<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exposition touching al the bokes of holie Scripture, and their excellencie</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1553</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3033.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120619</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855814</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855814</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21317</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16120)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21317)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 737:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exposition touching al the bokes of holie Scripture, and their excellencie</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[108+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Richardi Graftoni Reginæ a typographia excusum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini. M.D.LIII. [1553]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from heading, B1r.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The dignitie of the Scripture.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 3033a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: B-H (-H7,8, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; all before B1 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Criticism, interpretation, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on touching al the bokes of holie Scripture, and their excellencie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE wiſedome of God crieth in the wiſeſte of mortalle menne Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Prouerbes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to al men of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and Ages, ſaiyng. <hi>Geue eare, for I will ſpeake of principall matiers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prouer. viii.</note> 
               <hi>and the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my lippes ſhalbe to ſhewe out thinges that bee right. Depely dooe I muſe vpon the trueth, and vngodlineſse to my lippes is moſte abominable. In Righteouſneſſe are all the woordes of my mouthe: curſedneſſe, nor frowardneſſe in theim is none. Readie, and eaſie thei are to them that liſt to lerne and to theim that will finde knowelege, right, and plaine. With me is counſaile, and preſeruatione: With me is ſtrength, and vnderſtanding. Kinges through me dooe reigne, and Counſailours decree that is good, and iuſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:2"/>
            <p>When theſe thinges be ſo, I meruail what eiuil ſpirite driueth thoſe menne, whiche diſdeine the moſt ſacred Bibles the onely founteine, the moſt plentifull and richeſt treaſaurie of true wiſedom &amp; be madde vpon falſe, and countrefaict wiſedome. For a man maie finde at this daie, emong great ſtudentes not a fewe, whiche wholie geuen (&amp; al their whole life) to the colours, &amp; deceiptes of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie bothe dooe lothe the name of the Bibles, and when thei heare them ſpoken of, be readie to fal into an horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble quaking, and ſhiuering. I wys (thei ſaie) there wanteth Learning, and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence in theim, and that thei hate the rude, and foule barbaritie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Bibles Eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note>And yeat forſothe merueil it is, that thei ſhoulde ſette vp Eloquence before theim, as a rule to liue by, and a marke wherunto thei woulde directe all their whole minde, and ſtudie. In deede that wiſe menne oughte to loke for an other thing in this life, euen their very owne Philoſophiers themſelues dooe teſtifie <hi>Marcus Cicero</hi> the prince of Eloquence, of a Philoſopher doeth not require Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.
<pb facs="tcp:21317:2"/> For in his firſte booke, <hi>De fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus bonorum, &amp; malorum.</hi> ſpeaking of Epicure: <hi>The talke of this Philoſopher, ſaith he, diſpleaſeth me not, for he can vtter in woordes whatſoeuer he will, and ſpeaketh plainly to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande: And yeat a Philoſopher, if he bring Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, I will not deſpiſe it: If he bring none, I will not greatly craue it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why now be theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more hard vnto vs, then Cicero? Dooe thei not know that in our Bibles the heauenly philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy is taught euen after the capacitie of the common people? And Cicero pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth plainlie, that Eloquence without wiſedome is very hurtful. It behoueth then to couet wiſedome rather then E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, namely whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe If ſame <hi>Cicero</hi> in a booke called <hi>Partitiones oratoriae</hi> dooth define Eloquence to be nothing els the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeking ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore whoſoeuer is deſtitute of wiſedom though he haue a faire, &amp; a redie tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to talke gaily, yeat ſhal he be called but a talker, &amp; not eloquent. For as to ſpeake, and ſpeake wiſely is not all one, no more is all one, talking, and Eloquence Menne vnaduiſed and not wel in their wittes poure out many woordes many
<pb facs="tcp:21317:3"/> times withoute reaſon nothing to the purpoſe, and cleane contrarie to al con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience,<note place="margin">True eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> and comelineſſe. But a wiſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t man is no waſter of wordes, but ſpeaketh ſoche as doe profite, &amp; ſerue to that ende whereunto thei be appoincted, and he ſo ſpeaketh theim as he ought to dooe, whether it be with many, or with fewe, with learned, or vnlearned, with his matche, with his worſe, or with his better, the comelineſſe of time, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce alwaies obſerued. And within theſe limites haue the heathen maſters of elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in true eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce But ſithens no writers haue been leſſe waſters of woordes, then the holy auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, whiche minded onely thinges profitable, &amp; to a certeine ende, that is, al to obteine bleſſedneſſe, to liue quietlie, iuſtlie, and honeſtlie, and haue alſo ſet foorth thoſe thinges in a plaine, &amp; clere faſhion of ſpeaking: I dare ſaie boldlie and trulie, that onely the writers of the Bibles haue vſed true eloquence, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thing, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vaine louers of deceiptfull philoſophy ſhal not be able to proue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, except thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before ouerthrowe the
<pb facs="tcp:21317:3"/> deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of eloquence, whiche we haue brought out eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their owne auctours or els ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> manifeſtly ſhew y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our writers be not ſoche, as we ſaie for, which as by good argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes thei ſhal neuer proue, ſo aſſone as thei ſhalbe willing to dooe it, thei ſhal ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in daungier of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, ſacrilege, and high treaſon to God</p>
            <p>S. Auguſtine alſo in his .iii. booke, &amp; vi. Cha. <hi>De doctrina Chriſtiana: <hi>I dare ſaie</hi>
               </hi> (ſaieth he) <hi>that al whiche well vnderſtande what the holie writers theimſelues doe ſpeake, doe therewith vnderſtande alſo, that thei ought not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny otherwiſe to ſpeake. For there is ſome Eloquence whiche better becommeth young menne, and ſome that better becommeth olde, and is not then woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to bee called Eloquence, if it agree not to the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſpeaketh: So is there other that beſemeth men of high aucthoritie, and that be in dede moſt diuine, and excellente.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND with this Eloquence ſpake thei whiche wrote the Bible, neither doeth any other Eloquence become the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor this any other, but it is mete euen for them alone: and the lower it ſemeth to ſome, ſomoche the higher it riſeth, not in proude, and loftie wordes, but in
<pb facs="tcp:21317:4"/> ſoundneſſe of graue &amp; ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cial matier But the Hebruiſh maners of ſpeaking greue the tender eares of theſe learned men,<note place="margin">Hebruiſh phra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> and ſeme vnto the latines, that is, to deintie, and delicate perſones ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry harde, rude, and in no wiſe to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biden: yea I wis becauſe a fine ſofte ſtile falling, and ſounding ſwetely, in euery poinct, and delighting vs with pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Harmonie is that higheſt <hi>good thing</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che all menne oughte to deſire, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie regarde, without the whiche, yea the beſt thinges muſt be counted woorſt forworne, and naught. Lo here our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialitie, and malice ſheweth it ſelf moſt of all. For not onely the Hebrue toung hath her facions of ſpeaking, but the Grekes, and Latines haue theirs alſo. whiche hetherto no man hath diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, nor diſbeautified.</p>
            <p>Moreouer many haue written, and that largelie of the conſtructions, and propreties of Speache vſed bothe in the Greke, and Latine toungue, many haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Schemes, and tropes. In the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bee occupied, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lerne, and conne without booke, and with theim to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>browder
<pb facs="tcp:21317:4"/> our oration, is compted a very goodly thing. In theſe tongues no man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaineth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> facions of ſpeche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei be veri rare, &amp; ſeldomely vſed. Only the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage of god for her owne maners of ſpeaking, for her owne figures ſtraunge to our hearing, ſemeth fowle, ouglie, &amp; lotheſome: and wote you why? Verely euen for that vnto the olde Adam, al is counted vile, whatſoeuer is pure, &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie, &amp; what is ferrefet, vncleane, and filthie, that pleaſeth rightwel, &amp; is wel allowed. Plato is tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated into the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, Ariſtotle is tranſlated, ſo is Lucian, Plutarche, Iſocrates, and a great many of Greke Epigrammes. In the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what was rugged is made ſmothe, what was harde is made eaſie, what ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not wel, is wel knit together, what was out of courſe, is ſet in good order, &amp; brought to good Latine, that baſe was before. Now if the Hebruiſh maners of ſpeaking, and endicting do ſo greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pleaſe you, why doe you not prepare for vs Latine Bibles? ſurely euen becauſe the writinges of Paganes do pleaſe you better: What a thing is this? To en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our Subſtaunce, wee ſende our
<pb facs="tcp:21317:5"/> children into Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, into Italie, &amp; into the fartheſt partes of Spaine to learne perfectlie the languages of thoſe naci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that thei may the better, &amp; the more readilie traffique with the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chemen, Italians, &amp; ſpaniardes. Here we ſpare for no labour, we ſpare for no coſt, &amp; all is counted ſweete &amp; profitable. Only to learne the holie tong, to accuſtome our ſelues to her maners of ſpeaking, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che bee ſomewhat ſtraunge vnto vs, is thought painfull, &amp; vnprofitable, and a thing in no wiſe mete for gentle wittes Lo thus in dede doeth our malice ſhewe it ſelf. Verely if to learne holie thinges we did beſtowe yea but half the time, &amp; diligence, whiche it greueth vs not to waſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> matiers nothing worth, holie ſcripture ſhold of vs be leſſe deſpiſed, &amp; more ſhould be liked her facio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, though ſeldome in vſe, yeat very cunning, &amp; cleckelie. Now touching the lerning in holi ſcripture, I ſe not what other thing true learning is, then very Wiſedome, neither what wiſedome is other then very philoſophie. For <hi>Cicero</hi> himſelf in his ſeconde boke <hi>De off.</hi> ſaieth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thei that deſire wiſedome are called Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, neither is Philoſophie anie thing els by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loue of wiſedome. And wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (as it is defined of the Philoſophers) is a ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Gods matiers and of mens, and of the cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes wherin thoſe thinges be conteined.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After which faſhion Plato alſo in the booke that he wrote <hi>De Philoſophia,</hi> ſheweth that the office of a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher is to know heauenlie thinges, and to gouerne worldelie matiers, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendyng in that one, Philoſophie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatiue, and in the other, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie actiue. For the Platoniſtes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide all Philoſophie into Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, actiue, and Sermocinal.<note place="margin">Diuiſion of Philoſophie after the Pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toniſtes.</note> Vnto Speculatiue thei haue appointed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſike, natural Philoſophie, &amp; the Mathematicalles: vnto actiue Ethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Political, and Economical: vnto Sermocinal Grammar, Logique, and Rhetorique. And by Sermocinal, thei thought an entraunce to be made into Philoſophie actiue and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templatiue, in which ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the exerciſe, &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of true wiſedome. Of theſe thinges Ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cero alſo maketh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his firſt boke <hi>De Academicis queſtionibus.</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:21317:6"/> if holie writte lacke learnyng, then lacketh it wiſedome alſo, that is, ſcience of godlie and worldlie matiers. Againe, if the holie bookes teache the knowlege of thinges perteinyng to god and man, then teache thei wiſedome, &amp; ſo conſequently true Philoſophie. But let vs ſe what thinges be entreated of, and taught in the Bibles, or this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie Philoſophie, that therwith alſo briefelie, and as it were by a ſhewe, it maie appere vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reader what thing he ſhould loke for by knowyng the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, &amp; how in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the goodneſſe of god hath ſet out to the worlde moſt aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great riches of his high know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege &amp; wiſdome. <hi>Biblia</hi> in the plural nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre onely,<note place="margin">Biblia.</note> are called volumes or bokes. For in Greke <hi>Biblos,</hi> or <hi>Biblio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> is a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume or boke. So this name is borowed of the Grecians, and geuen to the holie ſcripture, &amp; is as moche to ſaie as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie bookes, or the booke of holie thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. This ſelfe ſame holie booke is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a teſtament, and in dede a teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t both olde, and new. Sometime in holie writte,<note place="margin">Teſtament.</note> Teſtament is taken for the laſt wille, and ordinaunce of him that is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng.
<pb facs="tcp:21317:6"/> And after this ſpeakyng, we ſaie, he made his teſtament, that is, he teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the meanyng of his minde, &amp; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed how he woulde haue all thinges diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and ordered, and by a trope called <hi>Metalepſis</hi> Teſtament is taken for the thing it ſelfe that is bequethed,<note place="margin">Metalepſis</note> &amp; ſo for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geuenes of ſinnes is in holie ſcripture called a teſtament. This woorde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is vſed alſo for a league, or couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t For God hath bound him ſelfe vnto vs by a league, ſhewyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, bothe what we ſhoulde looke for of him, &amp; alſo what we our ſelues ought to dooe. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicions be, God wil be a true god, that is, a father in al ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie, &amp; ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifulnes to al men. And ther be bound to reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and worſhip this God for their God in faith, innocencie, &amp; charitie. And hitherto dooe belong al the promiſes: I am thy God, &amp; the god of thy ſeede after the. The ſede of the woman ſhal breake the head of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. In thy ſede all the tribes of the earth ſhal be bleſſed. Again hitherto per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tein al the preceptes of liuyng, ineſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie the .x. commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Thou ſhalt haue no ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g god before my face
<pb facs="tcp:21317:7"/> Be ye holie, for I alſo am holie. Loue thy neighboure as thy ſelfe. And this teſtament, and league, this ordinacion of God is vnchaungeable, is one, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting. For there was neuer at any time any moe then one onely churche, neuer but one onely true faieth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of ſaintes.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Queſtion.</note> How the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue we the names of old &amp; new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? Verely of the maner of ſhewyng,<note place="margin">Solution.</note> teachyng, &amp; deli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueryng it vnto vs. As touching the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſubſtaunce, it is but one onely. For whoſoeuer wel conſidereth what thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were taughte oure forefathers, he ſhal perceiue that thapoſtles of Chriſte haue taught vs none other.<note place="margin">Entent of the Bible.</note> To them it was ſhewed that there was one God, that he onely was to be worſhipped, &amp; that in ſpirite, innocencie, and faieth. Alſo that there is one only iuſtice, and rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption of the world, onely one prieſt and true ſacrifice, euen Ieſus Chriſte the ſonne of God, &amp; man. Immortalitie alſo of ſoules, &amp; riſyng again of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to be hoped for of God. And what other thinges haue the Apoſtles of the Lorde taught vs? So then touchyng
<pb facs="tcp:21317:7"/> the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of faieth, and of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, al one, and the very ſelfe ſame thing is taught to vs bothe. Now for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner howe all one, and the ſelfe ſame thing was taught vnto vs, and them, Paule writeth and ſaieth. <hi>Vnto our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers all thinges did chaunce in a figure, and to vs be thoſe thinges come without a figure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For God hath geuen Chriſt vnto vs, whiche is the perfection of the lawe, that now we ſhoulde worſhip as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and paſt, that is, complete, and ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>filled, that whiche our forefathers had in a ſhadowe, as yet to be fulfilled, or rather to be loked for. And thus is ſene the diuerſitie in the faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of teaching. Thei had figures, we haue the thing it ſelf. Thei reioiſed in outward thinges and ceremoniales, we without figures enioie ſpiritual thinges that were ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified. And hitherto perteineth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt hode of Aaron, and the diuers bloudie kindes of ſacrifices, the figures of the prieſthode and ſacrifice of Chriſte. And by this diuerſitie in teachyng, riſe theſe wordes, olde, and newe teſtament. For that teachyng, wherby our religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was
<pb facs="tcp:21317:8"/> taught our forefathers in types and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, is called the olde teſtament, but that which without figures deſcribeth and ſheweth vnto vs Chriſte the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lawe, is called the newe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, not therfore newe, becauſe the olde fathers knewe not Chriſte, but by conferryng &amp; ſettyng it together with the olde, and becauſe a new people, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation of gentiles is receiued into this league through Chriſt, &amp; prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng of the goſpel. And hereby now you maie the better perceiue howe the bible is called the olde &amp; new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For the ſelfe written bookes of the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles are no more the newe teſtament it ſelfe, then the tables &amp; writinges teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie, or of leagues, are the teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or league it ſelfe: and yet of all men be thei called the teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; league. Thus of the thing that thei doo deſcribe, thei take this name. Becauſe then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the former bokes of the Bibles be declared preceptes, promiſes, factes, rites, tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and diuers waies, wherby God hath inſtructed &amp; ledde mankinde in his teſtament, in his league, &amp; true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, therfore,<note place="margin">Olde teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</note> ſaie I, thei called it the old te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.
<pb facs="tcp:21317:8"/> And becauſe the latter bookes declare vnto vs how in Chriſt al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are fulfilled, made new, &amp; in dede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored again, how alſo a newe people gathered together of the Iewes &amp; gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils is ioigned into one bodie, &amp; in faith &amp; charitie worſhip God in Chriſt,<note place="margin">New teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</note> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were theſe bookes called the newe teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Touchyng the title &amp; purpoſe of our heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie philoſophie, thus moche haue we ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in general. After wil we brieflie expoune what matier is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ech boke ſeuerallie. But firſt wil I ſpeake ſomewhat of placyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bokes of the olde and new teſtament, and how thei ſtande in ordre.</p>
            <p>S. Hierome in the preface to the bokes of kinges, &amp; Daniel,<note place="margin">The numbre and ordre of the bookes of the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</note> ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the olde teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is diuided by the Hebrues into the lawe, the prophetes, &amp; holie bookes writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by holie men, called in greke <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giographa.</hi> So he nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth of the lawe .v. bokes: <hi>Geneſis, Exod. Leuiti. Numeri,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The firſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre.</note> 
               <hi>Deutero.</hi> &amp; this he maketh the firſt ordre. In the ſeconde, whiche he calleth of prophetes,<note place="margin">The ſeconde ordre.</note> he putteth .viij. bookes. Ioſue, Iudges, wherunto he ioigneth the little boke of
<pb facs="tcp:21317:9"/> Ruth, Samuel, Malachim, Eſaie, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie with his lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tations, Ezechiel, and the .xij. prophetes. He alſo hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that theſe .xii. prophetes be not nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred of the Hebrues, and the .lxx. inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretours in al one ordre, and the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretours to reken thus: Oſeas, Amos, Micheas, Ioel, Abdias, Ionas, Nahu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Abacuk, Sophonias, Haggeus, zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias, Malachias. The Hebrues to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this ordre. Oſeas, Ioel, Amos, Ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dias, Ionas, Micheas, Nahum, Aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuk, Sophonias, Haggeus, zacharias, Malachias. The bookes called <hi>Hagio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapha</hi> he rehearſeth .ix.<note place="margin">Hagiographa</note> Iob, the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes, whiche is comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in .v. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticions, and one volume, the Parables of Solomon, his Eccleſiaſtes, the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, the booke of Daniel, the Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Eſdras, to whiche is ioigned Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemias, and the boke of Eſter. Al theſe put together, he thinketh of tholde law to be gathered xxii. bokes. He warneth vs yet that there be ſome, which count the booke of Ruth, and the Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Ieremie emong Hagiographa, and ſet theim in this ordre. Firſt the
<pb facs="tcp:21317:9"/> boke of <hi>Paralipomenon</hi> whiche with vs is diuided into two bokes, then the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> the <hi>Prouerbes of Solomon</hi> nexte, after theim <hi>Iob. Ruth</hi> foloweth him, <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> hath the ſixte place, the <hi>Lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tacions of Hieremie</hi> the ſeuenth, the <hi>Canticles</hi> the eight, <hi>Eſther</hi> the ninthe, <hi>Daniel</hi> the tenthe. <hi>Eſdras</hi> and his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Nehemias</hi> the laſt. The holie writinges whiche be next in aucthority to the bokes of the firſt, &amp; ſeconde order, thoſe by likelihod thei called <hi>Hagiographae</hi> as firſt writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; made by holie men, the other aſcribe thei to God himſelf, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming him, and not man to be the maker of theim.<note place="margin">Bullingers minde tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching theſe bookes.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To ſpeake freely, as I thinke, I doe not ſee why by as good reaſon God maie not bee accoumpted to be the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of theſe bookes, aſwel as of thother and why thei of the firſte, and ſeconde order maie not in likewiſe be called <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giographa.</hi> Saincte Peter ſpeaking of all the Prophetes, aſwell of Dauid, Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, and Solomom, as of other: <hi>No prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in the Scripture</hi> (ſaieth he) <hi>hath any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate interpretacion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">ii. Peter. i</note> 
               <hi>For the holie Scripture came neuer by the wil of man, but holie men of GOD
<pb facs="tcp:21317:10"/> ſpake as thei were moued by the holie Ghoſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Verely that theſe bee of equall auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie with the other, it is proued part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by many Argumentes, and eſpecially by this, that the LORDE Ieſus, and the Apoſtles in teaching, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming true, and ſounde Religione, vſed aſwell the Teſtymonies of the Pſalmes, of Daniel, and other bookes emong thoſe called <hi>Hagiographa,</hi> As of Moſes, Eſaie, and other.</p>
            <p>There bee ſome, whiche of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers that the bookes treate of,<note place="margin">In other diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> diuide all the Olde Teſtamente into fower partes. Into the Lawe, Hiſtories, Preceptes of Wiſedome, and Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Of the Lawe, thei recken fiue Bookes, whiche bee well knowen to all menne. Thirtene of Hiſtories: <hi>Ioſue, Iudicum, Ruth:</hi> fower of the Kinges, two of <hi>Paralipomenon, Eſdras, Nehemias, Heſther,</hi> and <hi>Iob.</hi> Of wiſedome the count thoſe three moſte excellente of Solomon the wiſeſte of all mortall Menne: Into the Prophetes thei putte the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:10"/> the fower greate Prophetes, and the twelue leſſer.</p>
            <p>I wil not kepe from you the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemente of Ioſephus touching the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the Olde Teſtamente,<note place="margin">The iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus touching theſe bookes.</note> diſputing againſt Appion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There bee not with vs</hi> (ſaieth he) <hi>innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble volumes diſcording one with an other emong theimſelues: But there be onely twoo and twentte bookes whiche conteine the iuſte order of al times, whiche alſo are rightlie beleued to bee written throughe the inspiration of GODDE. Of them, fiue bee called the Bookes of MOYSES, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinyng Lawes of liuyng, the firſte Creacione of Manne, and his ofspringe vntill the death of Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes himſelfe. And from that time vnto Artax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erxes, whiche emong the Perſians reigned after Xerxes, the Prophetes, and ſoche as liued at thoſe daies haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thirtene bokes the actes that were dooen. The other fower teache Hymnes, &amp; praiſes to god wardes, preceptes &amp; rules of liuyng. From Artaxerxes vntill our time all thinges bee written, whiche yeat neither are woorthie ſo greate credite, nor ſo to bee eſtemed as are the firſte ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers: Euen for this verelie, that the Prophetes fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed not ſtill in one courſe one after other, nor
<pb facs="tcp:21317:11"/> throughly be knowen what thei were.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe woordes ſtreight waies he addeth, whiche greately ſetteth foorth the aucthoritie of the Scriptures. <hi>Hereby therefore it is plaine</hi> (ſaieth he) <hi>how reuerently we vſe our ſcriptures. For in ſo many hundred ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res comming, and going, neuer durſt any man put to, take awaie, nor chaunge anything: but into all men of our nation is this faieth in maner graffed. To beleue all theſe to be the decrees of GOD, and for euer to abide in theim, and for theim, (if the matier ſo require) gladlie to leaue their liues</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto be the woordes of <hi>Ioſephus</hi> And I moche allowe this Iudgemente of his touching the bookes of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: Whiche <hi>Ciprianus,</hi> or <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> (for ſo thinketh <hi>Caſſianus</hi> in the Seuenthe booke of the onely begotten) wel nighe folowing in thexpoſicion of the Crede, maketh ſoche an order of the holie boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes as hath ſemed alwaies vnto me beſt and plaineſt. He ſetteth together al the Hiſtoricall bookes, then the writinges of the prophetes, almoſte in this wiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The order of Ciprian, or Ruffinus</note>Firſte he putteth the fiue bookes of Moſes, next the Prophetes called of ſome the former Prophetes, that is,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:11"/> the booke of Ioſue, of Iudges, of Ruth twoo of Samuel, and two of Kinges. To theſe ſtreightwaies he ioigneth the other bookes of Hiſtories, two of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralipomenon, Heſter, and twoo of Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras. After theſe he ſetteth the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, whiche we call the greater. Eſaie, Ieremie, Ezechiel, and Daniel. To the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ioigneth the Bookes of the twelue leſſer, whoſe names are rehearſed afore Laſt of al he ſetteth the other excellent Bookes repleniſhed with all kinde of heauenlie doctrine. The booke of Iob, the Pſalmes, and thre bookes of Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, &amp; within this nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre both certein &amp; plaine he includeth al the Canonicall Bookes of the olde Teſtament. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther didde the Biſhoppe of the moſte auncient Churche of <hi>Sardis,</hi> nor that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent learned man <hi>Origenes</hi> doctour of the Apoſtolicall Schole at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> reken vp any moe vnto <hi>Melitus.</hi> Of that one <hi>Euſebius</hi> maketh mencion in the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werth booke, and fiue and twentie cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter <hi>Eccleſiaſticae Hiſtoriae,</hi> and of that other in the ſixth boke, &amp; eightenth Chapitre. Yet in placing them thei vſe
<pb facs="tcp:21317:12"/> not all one order, as after the diuerſitie of examplers, and wil of the Scriueners you maie finde (I doubte not) theſe holy Bookes otherwiſe ordred alſo: one ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that before, whiche an other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth behinde, moued not ſomoche by rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon as by wil, and pleaſure. But a wiſe reader will not paſſe greatly hereupon, knowing that wee ought principally to regarde not the order, but the matier. Neither woulde I my ſelfe haue ſtande ſo long herein, hadde I not wiſte ſome menne ſo earneſtly to require, and loke for ſoche an exacte, and curious hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of this matier.</p>
            <p>The newe Teſtamente is finiſhed in ſeuen and twentie bookes. For the Euangelicalle Hiſtorie is ſette foorth bothe in fower Bookes,<note place="margin">Numbre, and order of the bookes of the newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</note> and by fower Writers. The Actes of the Apoſtles are conteined in one Booke. The Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of Saincte Paule bee coumpted fowertene. To the Romaines one. To the Corinthians twoo. To the Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thianes, Epheſianes, Phillipianes, and Colloſſians one a piece. To the Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s twoo: As many to Timothie,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:12"/> one to Tite, one to Philemon, and one to the Hebrues. After theſe folowe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Epiſtles Canonicall. One of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, twoo of Peter, three of Ihon the Apoſtle, and one of Iudas. Laſte is the Apocalyps made, and publiſhed by Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtle. By theſe bookes the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the newe Teſtamente to bee ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perfeicte, all the auncient Writers, and the holieſt Doctours with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent dooe teſtifie, and agree. Saincte Hierome in thoſe his prefaces. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine in his ſeconde Booke, and eighte Chapitre, <hi>De Doctrina chriſtiana.</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prian alſo in thexpoſicion of the Crede Origene varieth nothing from theim, ſaue that hee ſheweth certeine Bookes to bee in this Canon, of whiche ſome menne haue ſomewhat doubted. As for the Epiſtle of Paule to the Hebrues. <hi>I ſaie</hi> (ſaieth he) <hi>As it hath been taught mee of mine Elders, that it is Paules vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and that all our forefathers haue ſo taken it.</hi> Thus ſaieth Euſebius in the ſixte boke the eighteenthe Chapitre <hi>De Eccleſiaſtica Hiſtoria:</hi> And he alſo folowing Origene writeth thus.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>To aſſigne, and marke out all the Canon of the newe Teſtamente, firſt lette vs ioigne together the fowerſquare heauenly Chariotte of all the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſebeus tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the new Teſtament</note> 
               <hi>Couple to theim the Actes of the Apoſtles, and after, the Epiſtles of Paule, whiche be plainly knowen to be fowertene had in aucthoritie. Yet am I not ignoraunte the Latines to bee in doubte tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes. Then ſet the firſt epiſtle of Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the firſt of Peter alſo. Of theſe neuer was there any doubte at all. There hath been of the Apocalyps, of the Epiſtle of Iames, of Iude, of the ſeconde of Peter, of the ſeconde, and thirde of Ihon, whether thei were his that was the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſte, or els ſome others of that name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe be the woordes of <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his thirde booke, the thirde, and fiue, and twentie Chapiters. But I haue proued elſwhere that the aucthoritie of holie ſcripture is not appaired by the doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſome, ſeing it is not confirmed, ratified, and eſtabliſhed by Depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and opiniones of Menne, but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued to bee infalliblie true by the moſte ſure Sentence, and approbation of almightie and euerlaſtyng GOD. In the librarie of the churche of Tigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:13"/> there is in the vpper part of the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, a verie olde and true exampler of the Bible written by hande, which pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth firſte the .vij. Epiſtles Canonical, euen in the ſame ordre that thei ſtande with vs. The epiſtle of Iames ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth firſt, Peter next, Iohn after, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iude, and the .xiiij. Epiſtles of Paule laſt, of whiche, that to the Hebrues ſtandeth hindemoſte. In that exampler the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſtes are ſet firſt, the Actes fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe nexte, laſt after al the Epiſtles is ſette the Apocalyps. And thus moche haue we ſpoken, touchyng the numbre, ordre, and diſtinction of the bokes of the moſte ſacred Bible. Now come we to the argumentes and briefe expoſitions of eche booke ſeuerallie of either Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.<note place="margin">Moſes.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Moſes, as a golden co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duit, and firſte father, by whom the heauenlie doctrine is tranſlated from Godde to man, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending all vertue, and true wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in fiue bookes, hath taught the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame, and whatſoeuer he hath deſcribed from the creacion of the worlde vntill his owne time, with ſoche diligence,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:14"/> trueth, and vprightneſſe, that he ſemeth none otherwiſe to haue ſet it out, then he had receiued from aboue, and by the ſecrete inſpiration of the holie ghoſt. As for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe it ſelfe, as it was deliuered him from god, ſo did he publiſhe, &amp; ſend it abroade. Wherunto he ioigned the actes of .xl. yeres, whiche ſpace Iſrael wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred in deſert, him ſelf being a great part of thoſe thinges, that there were dooen, and ſeen. Theſe bookes conteine the hiſtorie of two thouſande, fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and ſeuentie yeares, wherof the <hi>Geneſis</hi> hath .ij.M..iij.c. &amp; .xc. For fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam to the fludde are M.vi.c.lvi. yeres From the fludde vnto Abrahams going out of Chaldee. ccc.lxiij. From thence vnto the death of Ioſeph .cc.xc. In <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> be the reſt of their afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and the actes of their going out in the firſt yere The other .iii. bokes make vp the ſpace of xl. yeres, in whiche thei wandred in deſert, and al this put together maketh ij.M.v.c.lxx. yeres.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Geneſis.</note>The firſt booke declareth the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng and cauſes of all thinges, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the creation of man, how it was fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:21317:14"/> the beginnyng, how he fell and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored again, how all men came of one, and being diſperſed through the world, by enormeous faultes angred God, and cauſed the fludde to come vpon them. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, how thei that were ſaued in the ſame, gaue the beginnyng to all king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: laſt, of Abraham, Iſaac, and Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob holie Prophetes, whiche liued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the lawe written in tables, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, condicions, maners, religion, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table dedes and ſaiynges be diſcribed, and how thei deſcended out of the lande of Chanaan into Egipt, For theſe and other good men, this firſt boke of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes was called of ſome, <hi>The booke of iuſte men.</hi> Yet with vs and our elders hath their naming preuailed, whiche called it <hi>Geneſis,</hi> doubtleſſe of the generation and beginnyng of al thinges, at which Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes beginneth his booke.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde boke declareth how the Iſraelites oppreſſed in Egipt by Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao,<note place="margin">Exodus</note> &amp; deliuered by their capitain Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, were ledde into deſert through the redde ſea, how thei fought againſt the Amalechites, &amp; were fedde with breade
<pb facs="tcp:21317:15"/> that rained downe from heauen, how at the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God thei did create a Magiſtrate, and at the laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued lawes alſo, deſcribyng, ſettyng out, and commaundyng true religion, holie maners, rites, ceremonies, and finallie al due and good ordre in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune wealthe. Here alſo is touched a little their ſhamefull offence, that thei did in worſhippyng the golden calfe. And of their commyng out of Egipte, whereof it principallie treateth, this booke is called <hi>Exodus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Leuiticus.</note>Vnto this ioigneth <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of the Leuitical miniſteries, which it teacheth. It ſheweth ſundry kindes of ſacrifices, vowes, pollucions, infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, general cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyng of ſinnes, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful &amp; vnlawful mariages, &amp; like other. It ſpeaketh a little of ciuill Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, but ſpeciallie of holie rites, or cuſtomes, and, as we might ſaie, the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes or canon lawes. Here maie we ſee how vertuous and learned prieſtes ought to be. All the miſteries of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, the prieſthode &amp; ſacrifice of Chriſt, his vertue &amp; power, yea, and our whole
<pb facs="tcp:21317:15"/> rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> couertlie wrapped in figures, is here throughlie conteined.</p>
            <p>¶The fourth booke is called <hi>Numeri</hi> peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture of this,<note place="margin">Numeri.</note> that in it the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſrael are nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred. It declareth the actes from the ſecond yere of their going out of Egipt, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the death of Moſes. In it be many notable exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of ſondrie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mocions, &amp; rufflinges emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g rebellious people. There is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed what euill ende ſedicious perſones come vnto, &amp; what maruellous chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces happen to the rulers them ſelues.</p>
            <p>Moſes of all menne moſte conſtant and pacient ſuffred vntollerable thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges dooen to him, bothe by his owne people, and other foreins to, and yet he him ſelfe is not fautleſſe neither. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinges are in this boke, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine to religion, and ciuil gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſpeciallie this: That biſhoppes ought not to flie from intermedlyng wyth matiers of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale, nor a ciuil officer to paſſe little vpon religion. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt at the ende be deſcribed great bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes, and certaine lawes are declared at large in the great plaine of Moab.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:16"/>
            <p>The fift and laſt booke is called <hi>Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teronomium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deuterono.</note> or ſeconde lawe, and as you woulde ſaie, The lawe expouned now the ſecond time. This is added of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vnto the other afore, as a briefe of all heauenlie Philoſophie. In it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined all that euer ſerueth to liue wel and vertuouſlie. The briefeneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is moche commended and ſet by, and is a plaine commentarie of the ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes. This Booke the Lorde woulde haue ſtill in the handes of his people, wherin he hath ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred all matiers, as to all degrees and ages thei maie be moſte mete and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient.<note place="margin">Ioſue.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The booke of Ioſue declareth prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallie the trueth of Goddes promiſe: How after the death of Moſes the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſrael by the leadyng of Ioſue (of whom the booke hath his name, as of the chiefe perſone) were brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lande of promiſe, the princes and people of the Cananites vainquiſhed &amp; deſtroied, in puniſhment for their great ſinnes. It hath a goodlie deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:21317:16"/> of the holie Lande, and ſheweth vnto vs an example of a verie good Prince, and obedient people. It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hiſtorie of .xxvi. yeres, or ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about.<note place="margin">Iudges.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Booke of Iudges taketh his name of the Iudges of Iſrael, whoſe actes and gouernaunce it declareth. And countyng Ioſue him ſelfe, there were emong the people thirtene Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, not as Kinges, and Monarches, but paſtours, preſidentes, and conſuls of free people. Here is ſet out a fre ſtate with many chaunges, victories, ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Oppreſſions, Deliueries, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and commocions. Alſo the mutabilitie of the commons alwaies ready to the worſt, diuerſe heauie chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the fight betwixt religion, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticion is here declared. It is a mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of that weale publique where is no head officer, but euerie man folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth what liketh him beſt, &amp; it ſheweth what euil end that to moche libertie co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enſueth ciuill battail,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:17"/> and deſtruction within theim ſelues. The hiſtorie is of .cccxxxvi. yeares, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countyng hereunto the time of Ioſue, and .xxiiij. yeres out of the miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Helie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ruthe.</note>The little booke of Ruth toke the name of the chiefe perſon. It treateth of no high matier, but ſheweth how after harde happes, and greuous te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations cometh a merie ende: and that vertue is rewarded, if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue ſtil in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and refuſe not honeſt labour. It hath a rehearſall of Dauids, or rather of Meſſias kinred very profitable for that that foloweth, and the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the promiſe of God. This hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie perteineth to the times of the Iudges.</p>
            <p>After this folowe .ij. bokes of Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,<note place="margin">Samuel and Kinges.</note> and .ii. bookes of kinges, a woorke of many and ſondrie matiers, very profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and full of learnyng. By moſte notable examples in them, be declared and confirmed the lawes, and promiſes of GOD. Out of theim alſo are made the Pſalmes, and homelies of the Prophetes. To be ſhorte, emong the
<pb facs="tcp:21317:17"/> beſt, goodlieſt, cunningeſt, and moſte ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie bookes of the Scripture theſe be not the laſte. The booke of Iudges ſheweth a ſtate of gouernaunce, where the people, or rather the chiefe emong them dooe beare rule. The Hiſtorie of Samuel, &amp; of the Kinges ſetteth out in his colours a Monarchie, or one highe gouernour, deſcribing not onely what a King is, but the facions alſo of al his Courte, and Kingdome, bee it good, or eiuell. Here maie you finde how lawes be chaunged, religion kept, or neglected, notable examples alſo of Vertue, and vice, of trueth, falſhod, prudence, iuſtice of princes, and prieſtes, bothe good, and badde. But who is hable in fewe woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the great varietie, &amp; profite of matiers in theſe bokes? The firſt chieflie deſcribeth the gouernaunce of Samuel, and Saul: The ſeconde of Dauid: the third painteth out the glorie of Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; how mightie kingdomes decaie except thei be mainteined by fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent loue of Godlineſſe, religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vertue, and concorde: So in the latter parte is ſhewed how the Kinges of the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:18"/> and Iewes, wounded, and killed eche other, how to their great coſt, and charge theie hiered the Egiptianes, and Aſſyrians to aide theim, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by gaue occaſione to inuade the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Iſrael, as it is declared in the fowerth booke: Where alſo you maie ſee, a litle before their captiuitie, how greate miſerie thei were in vnder <hi>Ieco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias,</hi> in the yere after the making of the worlde, three thouſande, fower hundred and thirtie. For the Hiſtorie of Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el comprehendeth an hundred, euen the twentie latter yeres of <hi>Heli.</hi> Fower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Samuel,</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> as it is in the Actes: and fowertie of <hi>Dauid.</hi> The two bookes of the Kinges vnto the Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie haue fower hundred twentie and ſixe yeres, and ſixe Monethes. To whiche, if you put the yeres of the Hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> and Iudges, you ſhall finde thre thouſand fower hundred, and thirtie yeres. Adde hereunto the ſeuenty of the Captiuitie in Babilone, and you ſhall haue from the twentie of <hi>HELI,</hi> fower hundred ninetie, and thre yeres, and ſixe monethes. But into the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre
<pb facs="tcp:21317:18"/> of ſeuentie yeres you muſte put the litle booke of <hi>Heſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeemeth,<note place="margin">Heſter.</note> thoſe thinges written of her to haue been dooen vnder <hi>Aſtiages,</hi> vnto whome the myghtie Monarche <hi>Euilmerodach,</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to the moſt victorious <hi>Nabuchodonozer,</hi> peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter had geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rule vpon thoſe people, whom the firſt chap. of <hi>Heſter</hi> ſpeketh of. The ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as far as wee can geſſe by the ninthe of <hi>Daniel</hi>) by likelihod was called <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> a worde of Regall dignitie, his proper name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Aſtiages,</hi> euen the very ſame that by the mothers ſide was graundfather to <hi>Darius,</hi> not <hi>Darius</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Hiſtaſpis,</hi> but of that auncient <hi>Median</hi> ſurnamed of <hi>Zenophon Cyaparis,</hi> which caried awaie <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him into <hi>Medea,</hi> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing .ii.c.xx. great Lordſhips. For .vii whiche his father <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> (as it is ſaid in the firſte Chapiter of <hi>Heſter</hi>) poſſeſſed were come vnto the <hi>Perſians,</hi> vnto whom at the laſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remnaunt alſo, were ſubiect after the death of <hi>Darius</hi> the <hi>Mede,</hi> whoſe Daughter <hi>Cyrus</hi> hadde maried, beyng Victour, Lorde, and Kinge of Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, Mede, and <hi>Perſia.</hi> But howſoeuer it
<pb facs="tcp:21317:19"/> be, in this booke is deſcribed the court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie life, fooliſhe, madde, and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious. There all thinges are gaie, and gallaunt, menne liue at pleaſure, and by riotous exceſſe loſe al thei haue. Many heauie chaunces, great penſifeneſſe, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill, and heinous treaſon is there alſo, The proude, and rebellious quene <hi>Vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi,</hi> is compared with the lowelie, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient <hi>Heſter. Aman</hi> is a paterne of an ambicious, vniuſt, and cruell tiraunte, from baſe, &amp; lowe degre enhaunſed into the toppe of highe dignitie, and foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with caſte downe headlong, ending his life on the gallowes, an example to vs of vnſtable fortune, and what thei ſhall come to, that geue cruell counſail. But <hi>Mardocheus</hi> repreſenteth a vertuous lord ſtanding on a ſure ground. through his wiſedome ſauing himſelfe, and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and by his prudente counſail doing moche good to other foreine Princes. As the litle Volume of Ruth, ſo this alſo taketh his name of the chiefe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone.</p>
            <p>Now folowe the Bookes, whiche <note place="margin">Eſdras</note>declare what happened to the people of
<pb facs="tcp:21317:19"/> GOD after their deliuerance. Eſdras euen at the firſte preacheth the trueth of Goddes promiſe. In captiuitie thei crie to the Lorde, and be heard. Seuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeres expired, by fauour of king Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, thei retourne into Iewrie, with Golde, and riche giftes to be put in the Temple being made vp again. Thei ſet vp an altare, and haſt them to building, but the worke was let two and fower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeres. At laſt vnder Darius the yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the Temple was finiſhed. Then came Eſdras, renewed the Lawes, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the faultes of the people, and prelates.</p>
            <p>After him came Nehemias,<note place="margin">Nehemias</note> and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Citie, eaſed the people from hard Exactions, burdennes, and vſuries, by witte, and Wiſedome holpe the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeines, and amended that was amiſſe. The Souldioures of Antichriſte, and their Craftes, whereby the buildinge might not go forwardes, is here plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet out, and how ware men ſhould be to ouercome thenemies of the people of GOD. This Hiſtorie conteineth thre ſcore and tenne yeres. From the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:21317:20"/> of <hi>Cyrus</hi> vnto the twentie of <hi>Darius</hi> are coumpted eight and fiftie yeres. From thence vnto the two and thirtie are .xij in whiche the walles were made vp.</p>
            <p>There remaineth the Chronicles, whiche the Grekes, and Latines di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide into two bookes called <hi>Paralipome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chronicles</note> For ſome thinges paſſed ouer in the former Hiſtorie of the Kinges bee here rehearſed, and ſpoken of more largelie. Yet ſure it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe be not the Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Iuda, and Iſrael, whiche many times bee mentioned in the Bookes of Kinges. Doubtleſſe thoſe wer moſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious commentaries of the actes of the kinges of Iuda, and Iſrael, now being loſt through waſtful time. Some thinke theſe to be a briefe of this excellente hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie, namely of the Kinges of Iuda. Thei profite moſte to the expoſition of the Prophetes. Thus hitherto haue we rehearſed all the bokes of the diuine hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie, whiche from the beginning of the worlde, vnto the building vp againe of the Citie of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is to the two and thirtie yere of Darius, is thre. M. iiii. C. lxxxviij. yeres, and vi. monethes.
<pb facs="tcp:21317:20"/> So many ſhal he finde, whoſoeuer wil diligently reade ouer the holie Hiſtorie: for we made this accoumpte by the ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the Patriarches, iudges, Dukes and Kinges. Neither maketh it any matier that Ioſephus, Euſebius, and many other folowe an other accoumpt. We haue folowed the holy writers, yea and the trueth it ſelf. Now to the other bokes of holie Scripture.</p>
            <p>Iob teacheth to beare paciently the croſſe of aduerſitie,<note place="margin">Iob</note> and that not by tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flyng preceptes of Philoſophie, but by wonderful conſideration of Goddes pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uidence. Firſt of al is the hiſtorie it ſelf: how there was a certeine good, and iuſt man broughte to greate aduerſitie, and what ſhoulde bee the merueilous mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of God in this caſe. After the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is diſcuſſed by a gret diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: laſt of all foloweth the croune, &amp; triumph of the victour. And in this boke is ſhewed more ſyncere philoſophie, then in al the bokes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer al the philoſophers wrote, of the which none hath tought any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g purely in this matier. <hi>The Epicures</hi> cal vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe to delectacion, &amp; pleaſure.
<pb facs="tcp:21317:21"/> The Peripatetiques counte ſickeneſſe, pouertie, reproche, and diſworſhippe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the greateſt eiuilles that can be. Certeine Stoiqnes doe counſaile men that be in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gier either to breake their owne neckes, either to hang, or kil them ſelues, or by ſome other violente death to ſhift fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their peine And other teache other thinges more fooliſhe.</p>
            <p>The booke of Pſalmes is an heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worke,<note place="margin">Pſalmes.</note> treating diuers matiers, and is both profitable, and pleaſaunte. It pleaſed God (whiche touched briefly al Sciences) to ſpeake a litle of Muſique alſo, and handle it purely, if perchaunce thereby men might be driuen from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, and wanton ſonges. So what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer cunning, and holie ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges Dauid and of his nacion other wiſemen, Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; preſtes haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of diuerſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers at diuerſe times, all thoſe woulde the moſt holie God ſhewe to the worlde at ones, in this boke. The pſalmes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine the praiſes of god, and godlineſſe: many exaumples alſo of calling vpon him, of praiyng, complaining, thankes geuing, and earneſte repenting.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:21"/>
            <p>Other bokes there be written of dedes and ſaiynges bothe good and badde, and of ſondry duties that men ſhould dooe. But in this you maie learne all facions of all kindes of life, and how the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes of God ought to behaue them ſelues, whatſoeuer chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This woord Pſalme ſignifieth a ſong, and this title, <hi>The booke of Pſalmes,</hi> is to ſaie, The bokes of ſonges.</p>
            <p>Touchyng Solomon,<note place="margin">Solomon.</note> thou readeſt in the thirde booke of kinges, &amp; fourth chapter. <hi>Solomon ſpake .iii.M. Prouerbes, and his ſonges were. M.v.</hi> But all thoſe we haue not. He hadde in his court to his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liars holie and learned menne, whiche through the prouidence of God gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of al thinges the beſte, and aſmoche as was mete for vs, &amp; haue written the ſame in .iij. bookes.</p>
            <p>The firſt is called Prouerbes,<note place="margin">Prouerbes.</note> or ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, ſhort in dede, but wittie &amp; ſwete, ſeruyng generallie to many thinges, and many men. In theſe he ſheweth good and euil, trueth, &amp; faſhode, what is to be deſired, and what to be eſchu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, addyng here and there diuerſe god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="tcp:21317:22"/> exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Some emong the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians haue defined a Prouerbe to be a briefe darke ſaiyng profitable to mans life: or worthie to be marked for ſome propre noueltie therin, as ſaieth E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes.</note>The ſeconde boke is called <hi>Eccleſiaſtes <hi>Eccleſia</hi>
               </hi> is a Greke woorde, and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth people called out to heare matiers of the common wealth. <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> is he that ſpeaketh, or reaſoneth openly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. So in this booke is imagined a great multitude of people to ſtande together contendyng emong the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues of the <hi>Higheſt good thing,</hi> and Solomon the preacher to come forthe, and condemne all their ſentences, ſaiyng. <hi>Vanitie of vanities, and all thinges vanitie.</hi> For in the firſte part of the Booke he entreateth that famous queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Summum bonum.</note> 
               <hi>Vvhat is that higheſt good thing,</hi> whiche in dede is, to be ioig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with God, and to haue the fruition of him for euer. Wherfore he replieth againſt them whiche ſaie, it is in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of many thinges, in pleaſure, in glorie, in excellencie, or richeſſe. Where alſo he ſheweth how theſe thinges may
<pb facs="tcp:21317:22"/> be well vſed. In the later chapiters he teacheth how we may iudge of good &amp; euil, of thinges to be deſired and eſchu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp; that by ſoche ſentences, as he had before in the Prouerbes.</p>
            <p>The thirde is the booke of Canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,<note place="margin">Canticles.</note> whiche is altogether allegorical. For in figuratiue ſpeache it teacheth, what, &amp; how good a thing it is to becou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pled with God, the higheſt good thing. god is imagined to be the huſband, and the faiethfull ſoulle the ſpouſe. Moche rehearſal is of loue, embracing, kiſſyng wel fauoredneſſe, and beaultie. Wherby is drawen out the nature, pleaſure, and ſtrength of loue, and ioignyng together with God, For it pleaſed his goodneſſe thus pretely to talke, and attemper him ſelfe to our affection, ſeing to man no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more ſwete, nor of greater ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gth then Loue. Let no man therfore conceiue with him ſelfe any foule, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, or filthie thing. All that is here, is holie, chaſte, and honeſt. It is called <hi>The ſong of ſonges.</hi> and as you woulde ſaie, the moſte excellente Songe, for that is the ſignification and ſtrengthe of
<pb facs="tcp:21317:23"/> the Hebrues doublyng. So thei ſaie. The holie of Holieſt, that is, the holieſt of all.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prophetes.</note>Now folowe the bokes, oracions, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Homelies, or declarations of the Prophetes. Theſe were diuine Poets and oratours, holie preachers, prieſtes, choſen men, maſters of liuyng, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous maners, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoche as in holineſſe of life, in feruentneſſe of ſpirite, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of minde, finally in moſt God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and effectuous eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, were aboue all other moſte excellent and maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. And in that time or middle age, many to haue floriſhed, it is plaine, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom were Samuel, Helias, Nathan, Heliſeus, Micheas the ſonne of Iemla, whoſe ſermons we haue not wholie, but ſo farre foorth as their ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges and doinges are deſcribed in the holie hiſtorie: yet as moche as is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, and enoughe for vs, we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, as it were by hande from one to another: that is .xvi. orations, of thoſe that were moſte excellent. All thei di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect all their ſaiynges, and dooynges to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon marke of the Bible. Partlie
<pb facs="tcp:21317:23"/> thei write hiſtories, partlie oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.<note place="margin">Ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of the Prophetes</note> In hiſtories thei ſhewe examples of liuing, faith, and vertue, of the might of God, his trueth and goodneſſe. In their ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thei teache what is the nature, &amp; diſpoſition of God, what his will is, what thinges he is pleaſed withal, how we ſhoulde ſerue him in faieth, veritie, iuſtice, holineſſe, and charitie. Thei ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, dehorte, and coumfort. Thei gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly rebuke ſinne, eſpeciallie brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of leagues, idolatrie, falſhode, mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, periurie, guile, deceipt, vſurie, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, iniurie, fornication, riot, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, and ſoche other enormities. Thei call vs by all meanes to repentaunce. Thei ſet before vs the promiſes, and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefites of God, thei threaten his anger, &amp; greuous puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: Again of Chriſt the ſede of Abraham, verie God, and man, of his bleſſynges, redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, kingdome, and all the miſterie therof, of the callyng alſo of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, puttyng awaie of the Iewes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and glorie of the Churche, thei talke and commune ſo plainlie, that a man woulde thinke thei wrote an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelical
<pb facs="tcp:21317:24"/> hiſtorie of thinges that were paſt, and not of thinges to come. And this is the common entent of all theſe holie prophetes, of whoſe bookes ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie I will now ſpeake a little.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eſaie.</note>Eſaie, one brought vp in the liberall ſciences did prophecie at the leaſt .lxx. yeres. For he floriſhed vnder Oſea, Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than, Achas, Ezechia, and Manaſſes. Howbeit though we take nothyng of the kingdome of Oſea, and Manaſſes, the Empire of the other kinges laſted lxi. yeres. In the .v. firſt chapters, he blameth the corrupt ſtate of his time, calling them to repentaunce. Then tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth he a Viſion that was ſhewed vnto him in the time of Iotha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: After that he ſetteth the Orations, whiche he made in the time of Achas. He ſheweth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to other forein nacions, what ſhould happen to them. Moreouer he diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie deſcribeth the notable battail of the Aſſyrians, a very great battail, &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull in dede: and what ſermons he made before the king, and the people, or euer this battaile beganne. And from the .xl. Chapter, he prophecieth deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce
<pb facs="tcp:21317:24"/> by king Cyrus, from the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie of Babilon, comfortyng the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God in their affliction, defending alwaies true religion, and improuyng falſe. At the laſt from the .xlix. chapter vnto the ende of the booke, he prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieth of Chriſt and the church ſo plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Hierome thought him rather to be called an Euangeliſt then a Prophet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For (ſaieth he) ſo euidentlie dothe he ſet out all the miſteries of Chriſte and the churche, that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> woulde thinke him to prophecie not of thinges to come, but to write an hiſtorie of thinges paſte.</hi> The ſame Hierome in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preface of his firſt boke vpon the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentaries of Eſai ſaith thus: <hi>Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinke that I can briefely prehende the argument of this volume, touchyng all the holie misteries of the Lorde, as well howe Emanuel borne of a Virgine did noble woorkes and miracles, as that being dead and buried, he roſe againe to ſaue all nacions of the worlde. What ſhould I ſpeake of his Logike, or of his Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie natural, and moral. What ſoeuer is of holie Scripture, what ſoeuer the tongue of man is hable to vtter, and witte to comprehende, in this booke it is included.</hi> Theſe be the wordes of. S. Hierome.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:25"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ieremie.</note>The Prophete Ieremie in his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng is not ſo faire and pleaſaunt, as Eſaie, but more homelie, and nere the capacitie of the common people, yet in ſentence as good. He was borne in a little ſtrete called Anathoi .iii. miles fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Citie, him ſelfe a Prieſt, and of the kinred of prieſtes, &amp; ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctified in his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe. He prophecieth being yet a verie yong man, &amp; as he ſaith him ſelf, he began in the .xiii. yere of Ioſias, and ceaſſed not by the ſpace of .xl. yeares, after the citie was deſtroyed. Yea, for his plaine preachyng, and free mouthe, he was ſtoned to death, and ſo gaue vp his ſpirite to the Lord. He rebuked the ſinnes vſed in his time, idolatrie, falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode, couetouſneſſe, fraude, crueltie, &amp; riote. He moued them to repentaunce, and amendment. He taught diligentlie faieth in God, and ſhewed theim how to liue. He ſpake alſo of their captiuitie, and comforted the ſorie, ſhewyng afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hande the deſtruction that ſhould come to the nacions borderers. He wrote al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a lamentation, wherin he bewaileth the ouerthrowe of that noble citie, and
<pb facs="tcp:21317:25"/> royall kingdome. Yeat in that kinde of writing appeare merueilous tokens of the iuſtice, and goodneſſe of God.<note place="margin">Ezechiel</note>
            </p>
            <p>Ezechiel, he alſo coming of Prieſtes was taken priſoner with Ieconias, and caried into Babilon: Where he taught the ſame thinges that holie Ieremie did in Iudea. Euery where, after the office of a prophete, he putteth in his writin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges common places of Chriſte. He alſo prophecieth againſt Tire, and other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, threatning vnto theim the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; iuſt puniſhment of God. He ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth moche in declaring the building vp again of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, &amp; newe citie: Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe propouning vnto vs the Miſteries of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche wrapped vp in couerture.</p>
            <p>Daniel being yeat but a very young man was led awaie into Babilon with Ieconias.<note place="margin">Daniel</note> This man deſcribed vnto vs very elega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly certein profitable, &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hiſtories of his time, the fight of true &amp; falſe wiſedome, of religion alſo, &amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He liued vntil the time of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> King of Perſia, being then .lxxx. ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res olde. He was a man of ſo great wiſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, that of him roſe this Prouerbe,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:26"/> 
               <hi>Wiſer then Daniel.</hi> whiche Ezechiel vſed in his .xxviij. Chapiter. Of al wiſemen he was called <hi>Polyhiſtor,</hi> that is, one that knewe many thinges. For like as he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſeth vp the fatall chaunces of all kingdomes, ſo in a brief hiſtorie or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie rather in fewe woordes he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth, and finiſheth that, whiche the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning, and curious writers of the Gentiles coulde not telle in many boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes how to beginne. Onely he openeth vnto vs truely the matiers of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians, Perſians, Macedonians, and Romaines, and declareth of Chriſt the euerlaſting kingdome. How Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte alſo ſhall riſe vp, what miſchief he ſhall woorke before at laſt he be deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troied. He ſheweth the deſtruction both of the Citie, and of the whole worlde, the daie of iudgement, the riſing againe of the bodies, and life euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The leſſer pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes</note>After folow the .xij. prophetes, whom we cal the leſſer, not for the ſmalneſſe of the matier, woorke, or learning, but for their breuitie, and becauſe in gretneſſe, length, and copie thei bee vnlike to the other .iiii. whom thei call the greater.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:26"/>
            <p>Oſeas ſtandeth firſte, ſine of wit,<note place="margin">Oſeas.</note> and vtterance, but ſomewhat brief, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore obſcure. He prophecieth moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the tenne Tribes, or Kingdome of Iſrael. Sometime he toucheth a litle the Tribe of Iuda. He rebuketh the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultes of the prieſtes, princes, and people ſinne, and Idolatrie, vpholding religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and goodneſſe. He warneth them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, leaſt thei all periſhe, and ſheweth that all nacions ſhalbe called.</p>
            <p>Ioel ſemeth to haue prophecied in the time of Ezechias, he, &amp; Eſaie together,<note place="margin">Ioel</note> after the deſtruction of the tenne tribes He moueth the kingdom of Iuda to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce. He ſetteth out the horrible daie of the Lorde, and their miſerie to come, whiche yeat might be auoided by amending their liues. Yeat after he ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſhalbe better with theim, and ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the ſignes of loue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche, of whiche <hi>Peter</hi> is an interpreter in chactes</p>
            <p>Amos neither a Prophete, nor the ſonne of a Prophete, not brought vp in any the liberall ſciences,<note place="margin">Amos</note> was but a rude homely vnlerned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet in few, &amp; ſharp wordes, he preached to the tenne tribes
<pb facs="tcp:21317:27"/> ſtill calling vpon repentaunce, as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prophetes did. And againſt the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions that were borderers, he ſpake ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grauely touching their ſinnes, and the iuſt puniſhment of GOD. He was ſore greued againſt the religious of the Ieroboams, and the wanton liuing of the prieſtes. He prophecied alſo of the calling of the Gentiles. He liued, and taughte, when the younger Ieroboam reigned in Iſrael, and King Oſias in Iuda, or Ieruſalem.</p>
            <p>Abdias reaſoneth againſt Idumea in the time of Achas King of Iſrael:<note place="margin">Abdias.</note> and though he bee the ſhorteſt of all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, yeat dooeth he comprehende in a ſumme al the chief pointes of true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: namely, that god is to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and that in loue, and charitie, doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng to our brother no wrong at all. For the lorde will reuenge it. He declareth ſaluation to be in Sion, euen in Chriſte and his faithful churche. He telleth the Idumeans aforehande that thei ſhoulde be deſtroied, with the cauſes why: and that nothing maie deliuer theim from the harmes hanging ouer their heddes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:27"/>
            <p>Ionas beareth the figure of Chriſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, and riſing again.<note place="margin">Ionas</note> Wherof the lord himſelf maketh mencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Math. He hath ſet out in a pure, and fine Hiſtorie the propretie, nature, and diſpoſicion of god, how mightie, how good, &amp; iuſt he is being god of the gentiles alſo, how vain the counſailes of men be, which are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt the lord, what true repenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unce is, how weake man is, and that the proude fleſhe, reaſone, and deuiſe of man woulde kepe her eſtimation and be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet by, yea, though it wer to the great hurt of other. He liued vnder Ieroboam king of Iſrael, being bothe a prophete, &amp; an Apoſtle of the Gentiles. Yet prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied he to his owne nacion alſo, as it is written in the fowerth boke of Kinges</p>
            <p>Micheas ſemeth to haue been the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of Eſaie:<note place="margin">Micheas.</note> verely thei liued both at one time, and had bothe al one ſupporter euen <hi>Ezechias</hi> a right verteous king. He cried out principallie againſt the .ij. tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, and then againſt the .x. He thretneth vnto theim vtter deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and calleth them to repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. He inueieth againſt falſe prophetes. He pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phecieth
<pb facs="tcp:21317:28"/> of redemption by Chriſt, of his kingdome, and of the calling of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. He teacheth euidently that Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation cometh through Chriſt to theim that beleue. and that the right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of God is true vertue</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Nahum</note>Nahum alſo flouriſhed vnder E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechias, and taught after Ionas. He preached againſte the Kingdome of the Aſſirians, and againſt Niniue their chief Citie. He maketh as though letters of defiance had been written by God, &amp; ſent vnto the Aſſirians, wherein Warre is proclaimed, &amp; that it is ſhewed, who, &amp; how mightie a God thenemy of the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuites</hi> is, &amp; for what cauſes he purpoſed to deſtroie that great citie, &amp; moſt aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent kingdom, &amp; he ſetteth out the maner and facion how he would deſtroie it. By whiche thinges he ſheweth a meruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous but a fearfull example, vnto al an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, mightie, bloudie kingdomes, and again a great coumfort vnto thoſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che are oppreſſed by tyrannie.</p>
            <p>It is likely that Abacuk was in the time of Manaſſes,<note place="margin">Abacuck</note> after Niniue was ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; about the beginning of the monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie
<pb facs="tcp:21317:28"/> of Babylon. But vnder this ciuill and vngracious King all true religion was quite gone, miſchief, and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion bare the bragge. Many were ſlain: innocent bloud was ſhead, all goodneſſe was baniſhed. Some thoughte that god was faſte in ſlepe, wherefore good men were not pleaſed, but ſpake ſomewhat ſharply. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> came foorth this prophete to comforte the ſorie, diſcourage the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt, and lift vp the weake: declaring that God would come ſhortly to reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge good mennes quereles by power of the Chaldees, whiche waxing proude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde meaſure ſhould be alſo deſtroied, and the Iewes ſent home againe: And that then in deede ſhould be perfourmed whiche was ſpoken, touching the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Meſſias, vnder whom ſhoulde be the golden worlde.</p>
            <p>Sophonias prophecied vnder Ioſias,<note place="margin">Sophonias</note> he, and Ieremie together. After the king by due reformation had ſet vp true reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe, there were not a few emong the heddes, and the people which deliting rather in ſuperſticion, loked and longed for a newe daie, and to ſe religion ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:29"/> and cleane put awaie. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he blameth their wickednes, &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth theim to repentaunce, ſhewing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehande that thei ſhould be puniſhed by the Babilonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and that yet he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had ſo great cauſe to be proude, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at length there ſhoulde come moche ſorow, and miſchief to him alſo. In the ende he ſaieth that Sion ſhould be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vp againe, and prophecieth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hagge</note>
               <hi>Haggeus</hi> vnder <hi>Darius Hiſtaspis,</hi> blameth the vnthankefulneſſe of the people ſent home again, &amp; their ſluggiſhnes in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vp the temple. He biddeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haſt forwardes the worke, &amp; not to leaue of, for feare of any enemies. In the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de he pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phecieth plainly of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Churche</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zacharie</hi> flouriſhed with <hi>Hagge,</hi> &amp; entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of all one matier,<note place="margin">Zacharie.</note> exhorting the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſpecially the rulers to builde vp the temple. This man ſawe the peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar deſtenies of the people of Iſrael, and writeth many thinges, as Daniel doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. He biddeth theim liue verteouſlie, writing many plaine Prophecies of Chriſte, and his Churche, wherein he
<pb facs="tcp:21317:29"/> is marueilous goſpellike. He ſpeaketh alſo of the times whiche folowed after Chriſtes aſcention.</p>
            <p>Malachie laſt of all,<note place="margin">Malachie.</note> whether he be the ſame zacharias, or Eſdras (as Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome thinketh) or any other excellent writer, chideth the prieſtes bitterlie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukyng their vnſaciable couetouſneſſe, ſlougthfull lecherie, and filthineſſe. He blameth alſo the people, and certaine light perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which murmured againſt God. Laſt of all, he ſpeaketh ſomewhat of Chriſtes time, and the daie of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in whiche euerie man ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded after his ſtudies and woorkes. This Prophete alſo ſemeth to haue taught vnder Darius.</p>
            <p>Howbeit from the .xxxii.<note place="margin">A ſupputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of times vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng of Chriſte.</note> yere of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, whiche fil in the thirde yere of the lxxii. Olympiade, we haue nothing of auncient, and Canonicall Scripture, vntil Chriſtes time: ſaue thoſe thinges whiche the Prophete Daniel with za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charie haue darkelie ſpoken of: how the Empire ſhould be tranſlated from the Perſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnto the Macedons: &amp; againe from theim vnto that foule beaſt <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rome.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:21317:30"/> the deſtroier of many kingdomes, and to the Princes of the ſame, vnder who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhoulde be borne the Lorde Chriſte, to make ſatiſfaction for the ſinnes of the worlde, to bring euerlaſtyng righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ioignyng the Gentiles vnto him, would forſake the Nacion of the Iewes, their temple and citie vtterlie deſtroied by the Romaines. And the Prophet makyng an accompt of theſe wonderfull thinges to come,<note place="margin">Daniel .ix.</note> ſaieth: <hi>Numbre from after the buildyng vp again of the citie, or the .xxxii. yere of Darius .lxix. ſeuens, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che make .cccc.lxxxiii. yeres. For .lxix. multiplied by the numbre of ſeuen, amounteth to ſo many, and thou ſhalt haue the time of Chriſtes incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion.</hi> With this accompt agree alſo the Olympiades of the Gentiles. One Olympias maketh .iiij. yeares. So the xxxij. yeare of Darius fell in the thirde yere of the .lxxij. Olympias. And the xlij. yeare of Octauius Auguſtus, in the whiche Chriſte was borne, was in the thirde yeare of the .cxciiii. Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias. Now if ye take awaie from .cxciiij thother .lxxij. yeres, there ſhal remaine rxxij. Olympiades, whiche if you will multiplie by the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of .iiij. you ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:21317:30"/> haue .cccclxxxviij. yeres, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of .lxix. ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, only .v. yeres ouer. For I ſaied .lxix. ſeuens did make .cccc.lxxxiij. yeres. But this little nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of .v. dooeth not darke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo great light. Thus we haue in our Bibles a ſure &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual hiſtorie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginnyng of the worlde vnto Chriſt.<note place="margin">Nota.</note> And doubtleſſe the wiſedome of God would haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto his church moe writers, had not theſe fewe notes of Daniel been thought ſufficient. And what auayled to rehearſe the Actes of thoſe times, being in dede bothe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blous &amp; nought. Thoſe thinges whiche Ioſephus in his bookes <hi>De Antiquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus,</hi> hath added to the Bible, doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the readers nothing at al. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deceites, lies, falſhode, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſhamefull dedes &amp; ſaiynges of the Iewyſhe biſhops, &amp; of Herode which in al kinde of miſchiefe bare the bel. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore by the very prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god, thactes of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſt corrupt &amp; abominable time, ſeme not to haue ben throughly writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but onely touched briefely of Daniel, &amp; zacharie. For ſo was it neceſſarie &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to vs Thus moch haue we ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:21317:31"/> touchyng the Canonicall Bookes of the olde teſtament, peraduenture ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what largelie, but not without profite. We will to theſe ioigne the matiers of the bookes of the newe teſtament.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Euangel.</note>Emong the writers therof, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſtes be firſt: thoſe be that write the hiſtorie of the Goſpel. <hi>Euangel</hi> is a newe woorde of this ſignification geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a new thing. For the olde writers called <hi>Euangelies</hi> rewardes that were geuen to menne that brought good ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges. Cicero writyng to his frende Atticus, ſaieth: <hi>O ſwete letters, for the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I confeſſe my ſelfe bounde to geue an Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel.</hi> But we vſe it not for the rewarde, but for the gladde tidynges it ſelfe: euen that from the father of heauen is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs a ſoonne, and with him all ioie and gladneſſe. For the Aungell of the lord in Luke crieth out vnto the ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdes. <hi>Feare not, for loe, I ſhewe vnto you great ioie, whiche ſhall come vnto all the people, becauſe now is borne vnto you a Sauiour, whiche is Chriſte Ieſus.</hi> Thus the Euangel ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto vs ioie and quietneſſe of mind, whiche cometh by this, that God hath
<pb facs="tcp:21317:31"/> ſent his Soonne a redemption of the worlde. Wherfore Paule defined the Goſpel: <hi>The power of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. i.</note> 
               <hi>for ſaluation to all beleuers, through his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> So thei that ſet out this matier of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, that Chriſte hath taught faieth, repentaunce, and redemed the worlde from the deuil, and al iniquitie, be called Euangeliſtes,<note place="margin">Euangeliſtes</note> of whiche we haue but foure, yet the name it ſelf may be extended to many.</p>
            <p>Of them the two firſt,<note place="margin">Mathew.</note> Mathew and Iohn, be witneſſes of that whiche thei ſawe and heard. For thoſe thinges that thei ſawe, thei ſhewe, and were a great part of the matier them ſelues, choſen of the Lorde Ieſus into the college of the Apoſtles. Mathewe wrote firſt (as ſome thinke) in the ninth yere after the Lordes aſcention. He ſheweth in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ordre the ſtocke and birthe of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſte, and what was dooen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhewed out him ſelfe, and toke vpon him his office of preaching open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and then what Diſciples he choſe, what kinde of teachyng he vſed, how great miracles he wrote, what bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites
<pb facs="tcp:21317:32"/> he did to the people openly &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatelie, howe he vſed his aduerſaries how his frendes, how he handled the weake, and how the obſtinate ſinners. He ſheweth his excellent vertues, his example of good liuyng, &amp; high auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. Laſt of all, how by his diſciple he was betraied to the Iewes, deliuered to the Gentiles, moſte cruellie ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled, &amp; at length alſo nayled vpon the croſſe, was dead and buried, roſe againe the thirde daie, ſhewed him ſelfe aliue to his frendes, &amp; after aſcended into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſendyng his Apoſtles abroade into the whole worlde, to preache ſaluation throughthe death of Chriſte, to all that woulde beleue, and geue theim ſelues wholie to God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iohn.</note>Iohn is thought late at the laſte to haue written, and put foorth his hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the woorde incarnate. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he hadde ſeen thoſe thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew had written, wherfore he thought as it were to make vp the matier, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the doctine of Chriſte, for ſoche thinges as Mathew ſemed either to haue paſſed ouer, or lightlie touched. Therefore theſe two hiſtories ioigned
<pb facs="tcp:21317:32"/> together, we haue a very full &amp; perfect declaration of all the dedes &amp; ſaiynges of Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Thei ſaie that Marke was the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of .ſ. Peter the Apoſtle.<note place="margin">Marke.</note> But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he was, in dede he ſhewed him ſelf verie wel learned, truſtie, &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For he knitteth the goſpel together ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry briefelie, and clarkelie, ſhewyng vnto vs, as it were an abridgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelical hiſtorie. Some ſaie he wrote the goſpel, as he had receiued it of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But it is vncertaine what time he put it foorth abroade.</p>
            <p>Luke was not an Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Luke.</note> but a diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles, &amp; one alwaies in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie, ſpeciallie in Paules. This ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrote .ij. bokes of the euangelical hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. In the firſt he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehendeth the ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges and dooynges of Chriſte, as did alſo Mathew and Marke.</p>
            <p>In the latter he ſheweth how and in what place Chriſt we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t out of the world and in what wiſe the holie ſpirite pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed did come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">Actes of the Apoſtica</note> how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church firſt began encreaſed, and grewe to the beſt: what was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of thapoſtles rites, or holie cuſtomes, religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; faith:
<pb facs="tcp:21317:33"/> who were falſe Prophetes, who true, what were the natures, deuiſes, and condicions of them bothe: What was the ſtudie of the worlde, and mindes of perſecutours, what c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces did folow theim, and how the Goſpel was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Many thinges be written of the Sermons and dedes of Peter, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtles, of the preachyng of Paule alſo, and his iourneies. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Booke is called the Actes of the Apoſtles. And all this Hiſtorie of them and the Goſpel conteineth about lx.<note place="margin">A ſuppucatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the times of the newe Teſtament</note> yeres. For Chriſte ſemed to be about xxxiij. yere olde, when <hi>Tiberius</hi> had reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned .xviij. yere. Paule in the .ij. yere of Nero came to Rome bounde, and was two yere priſoner at large. Vntill this time did <hi>Lucas</hi> write his hiſtorie, &amp; liuyng lxxxiiij yeres, died in the peace of God buried at Bithynia.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The hiſtorie of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect.</note>Now where ſome haue made me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cion of the Goſpel of <hi>Nicodemus, Thomas, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolomew,</hi> and certaine others, I wot not who, ſurelie it nothing perteineth to the perfection of the Canonical bokes. For Iohn him ſelf teſtifieth: <hi>Thoſe thinges
<pb facs="tcp:21317:33"/> whiche he hath written to ſuffice for the faith that may ſane vs.</hi> wherof ſpeaketh alſo the holy father Ciril. <hi>Not althinges (ſaith he) be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that the Lorde hath doen: but that whiche the writers thought to be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, aſwel for opinions, as for maner of liuing, that we ſhinyng in true faith, woorkes, and vertue, maie come to the Kingdome of heauen, through our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So when it was perceiued that al was write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche perteined to godlineſſe, it was thought neither neceſſary, nor wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thie the labor, either to put to any more, or to make any thing of newe. And if thei had, thei coulde not haue doen any other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ſet out alredie. This is euident in this that we haue. How litle diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (I prai you) is in the thre firſt? per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce the olde Fathers willed of one matier fower writers to remaine .ij. apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles, and .ij. their diſciples, that when al was dooen, it might be ſeen any larger inſtruction herein, or contrarie to this, nothing to auaile, no not if there ſhould riſe vp an hundred Writers, ſens theſe that we haue agree, al in one, and thoſe that ſhoulde folowe coulde write but the ſame. And to what purpoſe were it,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:34"/> in infinite volumes to entreate all one thing declared by fower witneſſes ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient before? For theſame entente al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it ſemeth that Luke wrote not al the Actes of al the apoſtles, ſins the reſt fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed none other waies, neither in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, nor in liuing: And that by thactes of one, or twoo, the reſidue maie bee iudged. Bee it therfore aſcribed to pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and not counted lacke, or imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feictneſſe, that the Hiſtorie of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and Apoſtles goeth hetherto, and no farther.</p>
            <p>Now folowe the Epiſtles written vnto diuerſe Congregations touching faith in Chriſte,<note place="margin">Thentent of the Epiſtles</note> true repentaunce, and innocencie of life, whiche in deede is the commune marke, and entent of theim all. The occaſions of theim be diuerſe, and ſo is the Argument, or matier. The firſte in ordre, and moſte excellent of all, is the Epiſtle written to the Romai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,<note place="margin">To the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines.</note> in whiche he ſo deſcribeth, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out the Goſpelle, as he preached it to the Iewes, and Gentiles. He diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of Sinne, and proueth al menne to be ſinners.<note place="margin">Sinne.</note> After he reaſoneth of Iuſtice
<pb facs="tcp:21317:34"/> or goodneſſe,<note place="margin">Iuſtice, or goodneſſe</note> &amp; ſheweth that onely tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the grace of Chriſte by faith, &amp; not by any workes, or merites, the beleuers to be iuſtified.<note place="margin">Grace, and faithe.</note> Then he declareth the effecte of Grace, and faithe, teaching the iuſtified to leade a penitente life, to kepe theimſelues from ſinne, to liue holilie,<note place="margin">Good liuing</note> and ſobrelie. He diſputeth of the lawe, and ſtrength therof, of the Nature,<note place="margin">Lawe, and ſtrength ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</note> and fight of man newe borne againe, of the calling of the Gentiles, the refuſing, and reſtoring the Iewes, at laſte he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmeth, and facioneth our maners with many good, and wholeſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes.</p>
            <p>In the firſte to the Corinthians he entreateth of diuers matiers principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly correcting the faultes of that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.<note place="margin">The firſt to the Corinthians</note> He reaſoneth againſt ſecular Philoſophie, for the ſimplicitie of the Goſpelle. He diſputeth of the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the woorde, and of the fruicte, and glorie therof, whiche ought to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to God alone. He rebuketh the ſhameful riotte, and lecherie of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthianes, ſpeaketh alſo of Mariage, Bigamie, and virginitie, willing them
<pb facs="tcp:21317:35"/> to auoide their ſtraunge facions in holy rites, and ſeruice of God, the true chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian vſe therof to be kepte, and reſtored againe, he ſpeaketh of diuers giftes of grace in the churche, of concorde, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, toungues, vſe of prophecie, reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the deadde, and many other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable thinges.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſeconde to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</note>The ſeconde Epiſtle is in maner of a defence, or anſwere to certein rebukes. In this he laieth the law, &amp; the Goſpel together. He ſheweth with what pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; great peril he preached the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and how wel thinges came to paſſe He ſpeaketh alſo of the almoſe to the poore. Laſte, he laieth many matiers of his owne, to defende his aucthoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt falſe Prophetes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To the Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</note>The Epiſtle to the Galathians, is in maner a Breuiarie of that to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines. He diſputeth of Iuſtificatione by faithe in Chriſte, againſt the Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by the lawe, and workes. He fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioneth alſo the life of theim that be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith. In the beginning he ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth moche of his vocation, and auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of his apoſtleſhip, whiche the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb facs="tcp:21317:35"/> of grace would haue had vtterlie to be diſanulled.</p>
            <p>Thepiſtle to the Epheſians is a brief but a notable exampler,<note place="margin">To the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</note> how he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Goſpel to the Gentiles. He teacheth the beleuers to be iuſtified by grace onely through faith, al ful perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to bee in Chriſte, and through him the gentiles alſo to be brought into the fauour of God. After be diuers exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions to good liuing.</p>
            <p>He warneth the Philippianes by a ſhorte Epiſtle ſent from the citie,<note place="margin">To the Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippiens</note> not to be offended with his impriſonment, but to go forwardes in the trueth, that thei had receiued, He deſireth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be al of one minde, and to beware of falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: chopping merites, and the law to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Goſpelle. In the ende he geueth Leſſons of vertue, an he doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth many times before.</p>
            <p>The Epiſtle to the Colloſſians is a breuiate of that to the Epheſians.<note place="margin">To the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians</note> It treateth of all one matier more brieflie In this he rebuketh ſharpely the falſe Apoſtles mingling Iewiſhneſſe with the Goſpel.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:36"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt to the Theſſaloniens</note>In the firſte to the Theſſalonianes he praiſeth their faith and conſtance, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to continue in theſame, to liue a pure, and a Chriſtian life, and not bewaile the deadde with ſoche out cries, and howling, as the Gentiles doe where alſo he reaſoneth of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectione, and daie of Iudgemente, of watching, and holines of the chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond to the Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</note>In the latter he paincteth out Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, and his Kingdome, and willeth that the dranes thoſe idle beaſtes ſhold eate no honie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt to Timothie</note>In the firſt Epiſtle to Timothie, he ſetteth before vs a very perfeicte exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler of an Euangelical Biſhop. He diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth of true, and falſe Doctrine: of the liuing, maners, and houſholde of a Biſhop, of his ſtudie, and care for Eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiaſticall matiers, of auoiding vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table queſtions, of wrangling, and intri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate bondes of couetouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſeconde to Timothie</note>In the ſeconde he committeth to his charge the defence of ſounde Doctrine, he remembreth him of his dutie, and not to be diſcouraged for any aduerſitie: he prophecieth of the departing awaie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:21317:36"/> the faieth in the latter daies.</p>
            <p>In the Epiſtle to Tite he repeateth in maner the ſelfe ſame thinges more briefly.<note place="margin">To Tite.</note> He ſheweth what men ſhoulde be made biſhoppes, teaching bothe you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and old their duties. He ſpeaketh much of the miſterie of Iuſtificacion by faith and commaundeth to flie Sophiſticalle queſtions, and incurable Heretiques.</p>
            <p>In a briefe Epiſtle, but very plaine,<note place="margin">To Philemon</note> cunning, and full of Chriſtian charitie, he deſireth Philemon to bee good to his Seruaunte Oneſimus, whiche had runne from him: And this he wrote at Rome being in priſone.</p>
            <p>The Epiſtle vnto the Hebrues is a goodly, and cunning example,<note place="margin">To the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues.</note> in what wiſe he preached Chriſt vnto the Iuiſhe nacion. Straite in the beginning he pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth by plaine teſtimonies of ſcripture that Ieſus Chriſte is very god, &amp; man, and therefore that his doctrine ſhoulde not be ſet light by. Alſo that he is the onely and true Prieſte, and euerlaſting ſacrifice, ſo that to pourge, &amp; put awaie ſinnes, ther nedeth neither any of Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s prieſtes, nor oblations. For he hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feict
<pb facs="tcp:21317:37"/> iuſtification, that poſſeſſeth Chriſte by faithe. He ſheweth that by faith all the ſainctes of the olde Teſtament plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God, and ſerued him in Pacience, charitie, &amp; innocencie of life, vnto whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che vertues, he exhorteth theim. In the ende he putteth certein rules of good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.<note place="margin">The Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie that paul learned in the third heauen.</note> And lo, this is the abridgement, and ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of that excellent Philoſophie whiche the Apoſtle Paule learned in the thirde Heauen, and left vnto vs in fowertene Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Seue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Epiſtles Canonical</note>The other .vij. bothe holie, and briefe, be called of our eldres Canonicall, and Catholike. Canonical, becauſe thei per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſcripture. Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, for that thei wer writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not vnto certeine churches, but vniuerſally to al Peter the Apoſtle wrote .ij.<note place="margin">The firſt of Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter</note> In the firſt he exhorteth to pacience, and ſtedfaſtnes in faithe. He teacheth maried folkes, maſters, ſeruauntes, prieſtes, and ſoche as be in aduerſitie to leade an holie life. In the latter he prophecieth of theſe laſte vnhappie times of Antichriſte,<note place="margin">The ſeconde of Peter:</note> warning vs to embrace the pure Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall Doctrine, and to keepe it faſte.
<pb facs="tcp:21317:37"/> Of like argument or matier is the epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Iude.<note place="margin">Iude.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Iames rebuketh the faultes of his time,<note place="margin">Iames.</note> teachyng true religion not to be in vaine bablyng, and boaſting of faith, but in Godlineſſe that bringeth foorth good woorkes plentifullie. He geueth alſo many holeſome, and neceſſarie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes of liuyng.</p>
            <p>Iohn Euangeliſte the welbeloued diſciple of the Lord wrote .iij. Epiſtles.<note place="margin">Thre Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of Iohn</note> In the firſt he ſpeaketh moche of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and pureneſſe of liuyng, the fruites of true faieth. In the ſeconde and the thirde he ſetteth out the ſame charitie, and trueth, biddyng vs to beware of Heretiques.</p>
            <p>The laſte booke written of the ſame Apoſtle hath a Greke name.<note place="margin">Apocalyps</note> It is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Apocalyps, or Reuelation. In this boke he prophecieth and ſetteth out, as the Lorde had opened vnto him, what thinges ſhoulde happen to the churche of GOD, euen to the worldes ende. Thou ſhalt find in it many thinges bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed of Ezechiel, Daniel, zacharie, and other prophetes. And thus it hath
<pb facs="tcp:21317:38"/> pleaſed the goodneſſe of God to warne his people in good ſeaſon of the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes that were to come, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei maie the more wiſelie prouide for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, and praie to God the more hartelie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Canonical bookes.</note>Moe bookes are not in the Canon of the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Neither is it great lie to be cared for, that ſome haue doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Epiſtle to the Hebrues, of the former Epiſtle of Peter, Iude, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and the Apocalyps. For what is it to vs, that a fewe corrupted with their owne affections haue doubted of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges certaine.<note place="margin">Nota.</note> It is to be beleued, theſe bookes of bothe the Teſtamentes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we haue reconed vp, to come of the ſpirite of God, to be written &amp; left to the churche by the prophetes and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of the Lord: &amp; in them to be taught all trueth, with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be mingled none errour nor lie. Of the olde fathers this was called Canonical Scripture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was geuen to vs of God for a rule of liuyng, and a trueth, by whiche we ought to trie all thinges, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to liue. The Hebrues cal their lawe, <hi>Thora,</hi> whiche name thei geue
<pb facs="tcp:21317:38"/> generallie to the woorde of God, and in dede to all the whole Scripture. <hi>Thora,</hi> ſignifieth a directorie to lead vs foorthe, of the whiche the Grecians alſo dooe ſeme to haue borowed that woorde of theirs, Canon, whiche you maie call, a lawe, or rule.</p>
            <p>There remaineth to ſpeake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the Eccleſiaſticall Bookes,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call bookes</note> of ſome called <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> the woorde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture not al agreyng to the thing. Sainct Hierome in <hi>Prologo Galeato</hi> after he hadde reconed vp .xxij. Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall bookes, ſaieth thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whatſoeuer is beſides theſe, muſt be put emong Apocrypha. Therefore the boke of wiſedome, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che commonlie is intituled to Solomon, the booke of Ieſu the Soonne of Sirach, Iudith, and To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie, are not in the Canon. I haue founde the firſte of the Machabees in Hebrue, The ſecond is in Greke, and that maie be proued euen by the very phraſe. &amp;c.</hi> Furthermore Saincte Auguſtine in the, xviij. booke, <hi>De ciuita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te dei,</hi> the .xxxvj. chapter, ſaieth: that the bookes of the Machabees, be taken of the churche for Canonical. And yet he him ſelf eſtemeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſo much, as he doeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which doubtles be canonical
<pb facs="tcp:21317:39"/> As you maie ſee in the ſeconde Booke xxxij. Chapter <hi>Contra Epiſtolas Gau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dentii,</hi> and againe in his ſeconde booke xviij. Chapter, <hi>De doctrina chriſtiana</hi> Howbeit ſainct Hierome in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, <hi>Super Prouerbia Solomonis. <hi>The churche in dede, ſaieth he, readeth the bookes of the Machabees, but yet dooeth not receiue them emong the canonical Scriptures.</hi>
               </hi> And ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of Baruch the Prophete, and the Epiſtle of Hieremie that is ioigned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, he ſheweth that thei are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in the Hebrue Canon, but onely in the common edition, and in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue that is before Daniel, he ſaieth: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neither the hiſtorie of Suſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> himne of the .iij. children, nor the tales of Bel, and the Dragon, be founde emong the Hebrues. But of the hiſtorie of Suſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Origene demed farre otherwiſe, &amp; gaue great credite vnto it, albeit he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth not, that in the Hebrue it is not founde. Hitherto haue I rehearſed what other menne haue thought of the Eccleſiaſtical bokes. Verely I ſuppoſe (ſauyng yet all other mennes iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei may right wel be called
<pb facs="tcp:21317:39"/> 
               <hi>Hagiographa,</hi> &amp; that yet thei ought not to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as good as the canonical bokes, nor to be of equal aucthoritie.<note place="margin">Difference betwixt Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crypha, and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call bookes</note> And I thinke plainelie that there ought a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie to be made betwixt the bookes Apocrypha, and Eccleſiaſtical. This Greke woorde <hi>Apocrypto</hi> ſignifieth to hide. So then Apocrypha,<note place="margin">Apocrypto. Bookes Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crypha.</note> be hidden or priuie bookes, whiche at home in dede or priuatelie to reade, it maie be lawful for euery man at his pleaſure, but in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon aſſembles, and ſpeciallie in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie temples, thei ought not to be read openlie, nor any man to be charged by aucthoritie of them. Of this ſort is the Goſpel of <hi>Nichodemus, Thomas,</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew,</hi> and many other moe of this marke: and of them is made rehearſal in the Canonicall decrees, the fiftenth diſtinction. Eccleſiaſtical bookes ſeme to be called thoſe,<note place="margin">Bookes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical.</note> which although thei be not in the Hebrue Canon, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thei teache good thinges, and are not contrarie to the bookes Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, the churche dooeth receiue, &amp; reade in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſaintes. And I am not the firſt that ſo thinketh. Theſame
<pb facs="tcp:21317:40"/> before me taught Ciprian or Rufine in the Expoſition of the Crede, whoſe woordes if any man will haue, be theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We muſte knowe that there be other bookes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Canonicall, whiche be called of our elders not Canonical, but Eccleſiaſtical, as is <hi>Sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Solomonis,</hi> and an other Sapientia whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is counted to be of Ieſu the ſoonne of Sirach, and is called emong the Latines by this generall name, Eccleſiaſticus, wherby not the aucthoure of the boke is ſignified, but the qualitie of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng. Of the ſame ſute is the booke of Tobie, and Iudith, and the bookes of the Machabees, al whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thei woulde in dede haue to be readde in the churches, but the aucthoritie of our faieth not by them to be confirmed. Other Scriptures thei cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Apocrypha, and woulde not haue them redde in the churches. Thus moche ſaieth Ciprian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore of the Eccleſiaſtical bookes, ſome teache hiſtories, and ſome prophecies, we will nowe as we goe, touche briefelie the matiers that thei treate of.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tobie.</note>Emong the hiſtories in a great ſorte of exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plers, the boke of Tobie ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth firſt, whiche in my minde teacheth to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre an houſholde moche better then ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:40"/> and Ariſtotle to. For he ſheweth all thinges, bothe by good preceptes, &amp; liuelie examples. The elder Tobie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the houſholde hath experience bothe of good fortune and badde, as wel in his bodie, as in his goodes, and yet in that chaunge of the worlde dooeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vnmete for a good houſekeper to dooe. In his greateſt pouertie &amp; trouble he kepeth ſtill the true worſhippyng of God, his innocent life and goodneſſe he chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth not, in no pointe ſekyng helpe by fraude and crafte to releue his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, yea him ſelfe being in very great nede yet doeth good to other, doing his dutie al that he can, &amp; helpyng to burie the deade, &amp; by moſte holie example oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupieth him ſelfe in his houſe, rulyng equallie his wife, his ſonne, and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie. Beſides this he maketh his teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he inſtructeth his ſoonne moſte perfectlie, he prouideth for his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he ſheweth him ſelfe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keful bothe to God and manne, and in euerie point dooeth the office of a good houſholder.</p>
            <p>But TOBIE the younger his Soonne, ſhewyng how children
<pb facs="tcp:21317:41"/> ſhould loue their parentes, firſt loueth and feareth God, obeieth reuerentlie his fathers commaundementes, being paineful, dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, curteous, ſobre, chaſte, and fearyng God in all thinges. In this boke is the honeſtie of mariage ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnelie ſette out, how vertuouſlie it ſhoulde be made and kept, how euil it frameth, if we come not to it with the feare of God. It ſheweth that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt waie to put all euil out of an hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſholde, is to ſtudie to be vertuous, and that the troubles of good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal haue a good ende, the wicked to periſhe for euer, with many other good thinges like to theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iudith.</note>The hiſtorie of Iudith, as of Tobie, hauyng the name of the chiefe perſon, ſetteth out the cruel tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, their pride, diſdeigne, and moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriftie ryot, preſumyng yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe verie great thinges of their owne ſtrength. So the maieſtie, the power, the valeantneſſe, the gorgeous pompe paſſyng the pride of the Perſians, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was in Holofernes lieutenant of the kinges armie, is here liuely painted
<pb facs="tcp:21317:41"/> Contrarie to him is ſette a lowlie Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, weake, and fraile, but verteous, and chaſte, fighting againſt that his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible power with Faieth, Praier, lowelineſſe, and Wiſedome. And being armed with theſe, warely taking vaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Capiteines ſurfite, luſt,, and pride, ſhe taketh this wicked man in his owne ſnare, and killeth him with his owne ſwearde. By this appeareth the merueilous will of God, exerciſing his ſeruauntes with the Croſſe, and not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering theim by and by, but at laſt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelie deſtroiyng all the ſtrength of the wicked, and laughing theim to ſcorne. Thus he alwaies ſheweth his mighte, deliuering all theim that truſt in him. Iudith praiſing the benefite of God te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs to be thankeful, and that God onely is to be called vpon, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, whiche in battaile geueth victorie, in peace ioie and felicitie.</p>
            <p>Suſanna is a very good exemplar of truſt, and vertue in maried women:<note place="margin">Suſanna.</note> the ſame teacheth that GOD kepeth the iuſt, and defendeth their innocencie, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth, and ſhameth the wicked forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catours,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:42"/> and adulterers, ſpecially nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtie iudges.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Bel, and the Dragon.</note>The contention betwene Daniel, and the prieſtes of Bel, for thoutward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp g of gods, &amp; idols, ſetteth out the nature of true, and falſe religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: of that one, the ſhameful craft and confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of that other the good ſimplicitie, &amp; victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. But ſuch as take this for a fable, let them beware wherupon thei take their grounde. The hiſtorie is ful of learning and profite.<note place="margin">The ſong of three children.</note> Thei alſo whiche ſaie, that the children in the fornace had ſcant ſo moche leaſure as to plaie, &amp; make ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſeme craftily to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne the matier By a like reaſon many thinges maie be ſet light by in the canonicall bokes. <hi>We reade that Ionas praied vnto the Lorde out of the bowelles of the fiſhe.</hi> This ſemeth not incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, the lorde being his comfort. Yet i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle felowes will diſpute what leaſure the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fornace. The himne it ſelf is a goodly praiſe of God, and his workes, and a mouing therunto.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">the thirde of Eſdras.</note>The thirde of Eſra. reherſeth certein thinges out of the .iiii. boke of kinges, and many matiers whiche are declared
<pb facs="tcp:21317:42"/> in Eſdras, and Nehemias, but more at large, with many goodly examples of vertue.</p>
            <p>The fowerth of Eſra. telleth viſions or reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teining diuers chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the people of god.<note place="margin">Fowerth of Eſdras</note> And although our forfathers haue ſet leſt by this boke, yet haue thei not vtterly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned it, for it ſerueth to a purpoſe &amp; is alſo profitable</p>
            <p>The fragmentes,<note place="margin">Fragmentes of Heſter</note> and reſidue of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſther geueth many propre examples of praier, and certeine other profitable thinges.</p>
            <p>The firſte booke of the Machabees for the fineneſſe of ſtile,<note place="margin">Firſt of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees</note> ſauoureth ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the olde Phraſe, that is of the Canonical ſcripture, and ſheweth vnto vs goodly exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of faith. For of faith manlineſſe, noble courage, temperance, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtaunce, loue to god, &amp; their countrie the noble childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that right excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lord <hi>Mattathias</hi> their father, are moſt liue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly preſidentes. Thei fight for their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treie, &amp; holie lawes againſt the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, with great ſucceſſe? Yeat abuſe thei not their victory. Firſt thei ſet vp again the right woorſhipping of God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe
<pb facs="tcp:21317:43"/> the common wealth whiche was far out of order. Hereby we maie lerne to feare God, and fight againſt infidels, all ſoche as by lawefull vocatione haue that Office committed vnto theim. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, and merueilous chaunces bee in this booke, wherin euidentlie appereth the goodneſſe of God, his trueth, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, equitie, Mercie, and many other thinges that the Scripture ſpeaketh of in him, how he defendeth his ſeruantes and puniſheth his enemies. This boke is of ſoche price, that great loſſe it wer for good men to lacke it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſeconde of Machabees</note>The ſeconde booke in ſtile is vnlike the other. It is full of Grekiſhe Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: neither haue the olde fathers ſo greatlie eſtemed it as the firſt. It repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth many thinges declared in the firſt, but more plainly. It conteineth the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſe Martyrdome of the ſeuen bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and the ſtedfaſt belief of the olde father Eleazer, mete to bee folowed of all good men, whiche thinges Cecilius Ciprianus in the exhortacione to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome ſpeaketh of largelie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Manaſſes</note>The confeſſion of Manaſſes ſheweth
<pb facs="tcp:21317:43"/> vnto vs the maner of true repentance, and iuſt confeſſione of our ſinnes to bee made before God.<note place="margin">Sapientia.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Emong other bokes whiche contein preceptes of liuing, <hi>Sapie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia</hi> is ſet firſt being in dede, as it is called, the wiſedom of Solomon, not that he was the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker thereof, but the wiſedome ſoche, as might beſeme Solomon. The Stile is pure, and fine: It teacheth, and praiſeth wiſedom, and telleth of what effect and ſtrength it is, and how moche to bee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured for. Herein he laudeth Godde highlie, whom to knowe is very wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. It rebuketh falſe wiſedome, and that deadlie poiſone Idolatrie, of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Lactantius ſpeaketh and ſaieth. <hi>There can be no woorſhipping of God where Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie is.</hi> It ſheweth many thinges that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to true wiſedome, which here thei maie ſee that liſt to learne.</p>
            <p>Eccleſiaſticus of Ieſu the ſonne of Sirach,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſticus.</note> hathe moche that is before in the prouerbes. He writeth more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, &amp; is not ſo hard. Here maie be lerned moral philoſophie moche better, &amp; with leſſe ieopardie then out of any Plato, or
<pb facs="tcp:21317:44"/> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> Almoſt at the ende is a goodlie praiſe of holie fathers, and their faith, wherunto peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture thapoſtle Paul had an yie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wrote the leuenth cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piter of thepiſtle to the hebrues, in whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che alſo he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth the faieth of our elders, not ſomoche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhoulde know it, as endeuour to folowe it. He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his worke with praiers to God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Baruch.</note>The prophet <hi>Baruch</hi> is moche alleged of the doctoures. He wrote a litle boke being in captiuitie at Babilon. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth God to be iuſt, and worthely to haue puniſhed the Iues, he knowlegeth their faultes, &amp; blameth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtubburne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He deſireth perdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, &amp; that God hauing pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his people, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt wolde bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> again into their countreie. Further to ſtirre vp faith in their hartes, he tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that Iſrael ſhalbe ſent home again</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Epiſtle of Ieremie</note>Thepiſtle of <hi>Ieremie</hi> put vnto <hi>Baruch</hi> warneth the captiues that thei tourne not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the true god, &amp; reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gods of <hi>Babylon.</hi> And therfore he greuouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buketh idolatrie, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the very God, &amp; ſerue him onely.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:44"/>
            <p>I thought good to adde hereunto that whiche <hi>Theodorus Bibliander</hi> hathe written to oure greatte profite of the bookes Eccleſiaſtical in his woorke <hi>De optimo genere interpreta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di hebraica</hi> in whiche he briefly toucheth bothe the effecte of the bokes,<note place="margin">The times of the bookes Ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical</note> and the times when thei were writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which we haue not ſet out: his woordes be theſe. <hi>The Eccleſiaſtical bookes alſo thei call <hi>Hagiographa:</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thei haue no fitte aucthoritie to ſtrengthen, and confirme thinges that come into contencion, as haue the Canonicall writinges, ye at are thei not reiected as APOCRYPHA ſoche as is the Prophecie of ELDAD, and MED AD.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apocrypha</note> 
               <hi>Thaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention of Moſes, the Apocalyps of Helyas, and many other like deuiſes of the Deuilles Spirite. But the Eccleſiaſticall bookes bee admitted bothe to bee taughte, and learned of faithfull people, &amp; of many ſo reuerenced, that ſome menne putte Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith in the order of Canonicall Scripture.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The times of theccleſiaſtical Bookes.</note> 
               <hi>We will rehearſe theim keping the due order of times whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei were written. Parte of theim conteine Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries from the time of Ezechias vnto the birthe of Pompeie, whiche firſte tooke from the Iewes their kingdome. Tobias tranſlated hy Saincte Hierome out of the Chaldee into Latine, as was Iudith alſo
<pb facs="tcp:21317:45"/> mencioneth thoſe thinges that wer doen emong the Aſſirians after the tenne Tribes were ledde into captiuitie, teaching by notable example, what loue ought to bee in parentes, children, and maried folkes. Iudith ſhewing the nature of faithfulneſse and conſtaunce, declareth that Bethulia was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged of Nabuchodonozors Lieutenaunte,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudith</note> 
               <hi>father to the great Nabuchodonozor, whiche tooke priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Ioachim, Ieconiam, and Zedechiam, &amp; howe it was deliuered by the meanes of the righte holie woman Iudith. And I am in doubte whether it was in that battaile in which Manaſses alſo king of Iuda was caried awaie into Aſsiria, &amp; ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie after ſente home againe. For while he ruled e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Medes, Dioces called alſo Arphaxat, builded the Citie Echatana in the Countrie of Medea. But I knowe that Ioſephus referreth theſe thinges to the time of Cambyſes. Damel hath the remenaunt of Suſanna, and the Dragon of Bel. In Heſter bee certeine thinges added vnto it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suſanna Bel. Heſter The thirde of Eſdras.</note> 
               <hi>The thirde of Eſdras repeateth ſomewhat of the paſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of Ioſias written in the bookes of Kinges, and of thoſe thinges whiche be in Eſra. and Nehemias after their retourne out of Babylon, minglyng ther with a goodly contentione of witte, and wiſedome, in whiche zorobabel hadde the victorie. The bokes of the Machabees declare the affliction of Iſrael,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:45"/> by Antiochus Epiphanes, and the Macedones, in whom is the euident figure of Antichriſte. Parte of the Eccleſiaſtical bookes treate of vertue and good liuyng.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baruch.</note> 
               <hi>Baruch gatheryng together the ſenten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of Eſaie, and Ieremie, whiche make to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profe of Idoles, rebuketh Idolatrie verie ſore.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fourth of Eſra.</note> 
               <hi>The fourth booke of Eſra hath diuers prophecies, and is verie moche in viſions, as is alſo Ezechiel, za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias, and Daniel. Ieſus the ſoonne of Sirach about the .cxxxviii. Olympiade put foorth his boke Eccleſiaſticus, whiche is called alſo Sapientia, and Hierome founde it in Hebrue intitled by the name of Parables.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</note> 
               <hi>It teacheth Philoſophie in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, whiche is a verie olde vſage, and in it be many thinges ſpoken of before in the Preacher, and in the Prouerbes of Solomon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sapientia</note> 
               <hi>The booke of wiſedome, whiche is aſcribed to Philo the moſte e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent of all the Iewes, and as cunnyng menne dooe ſaie, in maner an other Plato, doth more large<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, and in Grekiſhe eloquence declare ſoche thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as in the beginnyng of the Prouerbes dooe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine to the praiſe of true wiſedome. The praier of Manaſses whiche is not in the Greke examplers ſauoureth plainely of the Hebrue phraſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Manaſſes Praier</note> 
               <hi>Thus moche ſaieth our Theodorus.</hi> Now will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne to my purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt (O reader) as farre forth
<pb facs="tcp:21317:46"/> as we can ſhewe and comprehende in briefe expoſitions,<note place="margin">The darknes and errours of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers.</note> the riches, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple learnyng of our heauenlie Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie. Saie on now you our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries what maie be thought that we lacke, or what you thinke we ought to begge of that your Philoſophie? Vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if you will confeſſe the trueth, you muſt ſay, that we be deſtitute in no part of true learnyng &amp; wiſedome. I graunt in dede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the bible nothing is taught of that part of Philoſophie, whiche is called Sermocinal, neither of thinges natural, or artes Mathematical. For theſe be as it were handmaides to leade vs to the quene of all ſciences, &amp; teache vs that we maie be able to ſpeake with her, and learne true knowledge of thinges perteinyng to God &amp; man, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie the actes ſermonicall.<note place="margin">Moderate ſtudie of the ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces doeth helpe to wiſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome.</note> We dooe not condemne the ſobre &amp; moderate ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies herein, but confeſſe theim neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and moche helping to atteine wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Philoſophie learned in meaſure profiteth moche. Yet this we ſaie, that to knowe God, &amp; leade our liues vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie, not onely is taught in our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:46"/> but alſo more plainelie and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlye, then in all your writynges. For your Philoſophers haue written hereof darkelie, yea, and falſelie to in many poinctes. Ariſtotle whiche in this part is with you a King,<note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note> and in maner worſhipped for a GOD, hath for the nones darkened thoſe thinges whiche he wrote of Moral Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, yea, of naturall to. He vſed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo doubtfull ſentences, that might be bowed to whiche ſide you liſte, and as he checked all writers before him, ſo fearyng to be taunted againe, &amp; his ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges corrected of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that came after, he made ſure prouiſion in caſe he were caught, by one ſhifte or other to winde him ſelfe out. He wrote alſo vnto king Alexander, that none ſhoulde vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his commentaries, excepte he hadde hearde them redde of his owne mouthe at home in his houſe. He ſtudied for a kinde of enditynge more briefe and cutted then euer was any, that ſometime he ſemed rather to pointe to the matier, then ſpeake it out plainelie, whiche thing <hi>Lodouicus viues,</hi> a man
<pb facs="tcp:21317:47"/> of a ſharpe witte &amp; iudgment, right wel perceiued. In his moralles, he teacheth moche naughtineſſe, contrarie to right, reaſon,<note place="margin">Plato.</note> and our religion. But Plato, one leſſe corrupt then Ariſtotle, hath dooen ſo euill about the maieſtie of the eternal GOD, that he maketh all his Philoſophie worthelie ſuſpected. The trueth whiche he knew of the true god for feare he durſt not declare. I haue witneſſe hereof Iuſtine the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher and martire, in a warning that he geueth to the Gentiles, ſaiyng thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plato when he ſhould haue ſhewed the doctrine of Moſes, and other Prophetes touchyng one God, whiche he had learned in Egipte, fearyng that happened to Socrates, and to ſtirre vp againſt him ſome Anytus and Meliſsus to accuſe him of here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſie before the men of Athens, &amp; ſo to be poyſoned went about a variable &amp; crafty conueyed ſermon touching the Goddes, wherby their opinion might ſtande whiche thought there were many, and theirs alſo whiche thought the contrarie, as by his writynges maie eaſelie be ſeen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Loe the goodlie actes of theſe two Princes of the Philoſophers, and in maner their Goddes. What ſhould we
<pb facs="tcp:21317:47"/> loke for of the commune ſorte, ſeyng in theſe their chiefe lightes ſo great dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is founde. I trowe no man is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt what theſe blinde guides haue iudged touchyng the ſoule, what trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thei haue made, and howe foliſhelie babled therof. <hi>Of the higheſt good thing,</hi> as many be their opinions, as daies in the yere. Finallie, thei haue ſcarſe iudged rightlie of any thing that perteineth to bleſſedneſſe, and vertue: and yet folow we theſe buſſardes whollie geuen to worſhip and maruail at them, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at all the Bible: yea, we thinke no man learned in dede, except he be well ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the ſinkes of their filthy errours. Howe moche better and more wiſelie did thei whiche ſometime beyng noble men in Chriſtes churche, forſakyng the ſtudie of Philoſophie (wherin yet to this daie by all conſent, thei were moſt excellent) gaue them ſelues whollie to ſtudie the Bible our heauenlie Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie, and haſting awaie from enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lies, deceiptes, &amp; blindeneſſe, ioie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie came to the bright ſhinyng ſunne of trueth. I meane <hi>Origen, Iuſtine, Pante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21317:48"/> Ciprian and innumerable other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Philoſophers and Oratours, whoſe ſoulles now reſte and liue with the Lorde God eternal. I will not cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile any man therfore to folow thoſe blind teachers, or their erronious doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, wherin no pure nor certein thing maie be founde. I cal and exhort all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as loude and as hartelie as I can, to the moſt holie, and ſacred Bible. For mans hope &amp; ſaluation onely ſtandeth in that learnyng which the Bible teacheth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. All the right wiſedome that man hath,<note place="margin">Wherin all wiſedome reſteth.</note> reſteth in this one poinct, to know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge God for his owne God, and that through Chriſte, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the bookes of al the Philoſophers haue not ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo moche as one woorde, neither how by true faieth and ſure hope we ſhould cleue vnto him whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is knowen, and honour this moſt mightie Lorde &amp; bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull father, in charitie and innocencie of life. This is our determinacion and doctrine, this is our ful mind &amp; ſentence I teſtifie it therefore with as loude a voice as I can, I proclaime and warne
<pb facs="tcp:21317:48"/> you to kepe it. This is that, whiche al the Philoſophers haue ſought for all the daies of their life, and yet could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer faſten vpon it, nor holde it: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for becauſe ſekyng it a wrong waie, either thei helde a naughtie religion, or elles made no religion at all. Wherfore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie with al ſoche, which ſet not mans life in ordre, but diſtrouble it. For what teache thei, or whom dooe thei inſtruct whiche can not teache them ſelues? Whom can ſieke men heale, whom can blinde men guide? Shall we tarie till Socrates knowe ſomewhat, or Anaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras finde light in darkeneſſe, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocritus drawe trueth out of the wel, or Empedocles dilate the pathes of his minde, or Arceſilas and Carneades can ſee, fele, and perceiue? Beholde a voice from heauen teachyng the trueth, and ſhewyng a light brighter then the ſhinyng Sunne ſpeaketh in the Bible openlie, plainelie, and certainelie. Lette all therefore that care for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie wiſedome come hither. Will we hurt our ſelues, and linger to take it?
<pb facs="tcp:21317:49"/> You that will be wiſe and happie har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie voice, learne Ieſus Chriſte to be your iuſtice, and in him to be laied vp all the treaſure of Goddes high wiſedome and ſcience, learne the miſterie of your faieth, and natiuitie, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe worldly thinges, loue heauenlie, that after this miſerable and wretched life you maie come to the ioie that is prepared for you.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferring of the holie bokes with the prophan</note>But the pleaſant varietie of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane writers, and their propre caſt of teachyng dooeth moche delight theim. Well go to. Declare I praie you ſome of your gaie and goodlie colours. Thei teache wiſedome (ſaie thei) in pleaſant and fine diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, in ſwete dialoges and elegant epiſtles, as dooeth Plato, Ariſtotle, &amp; Seneca: In eloquent orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as Iſocrates, Cicero, and Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthenes, in dilectable fables &amp; allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: as Homere, and Virgil: in ſentences and Prouerbes bothe ſhorte and ſwete, as the ſeuen ſages of Grece, Chriſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus alſo, &amp; Diogenianus: in notable hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, as Herodotus, Halicarnaſſeus, Diodorus Siculus, and Liuius Pata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinus.
<pb facs="tcp:21317:49"/> But if theſe great boaſters of Gentile Aucthours were aſwell accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to holie writinges as thei are to prophane, thei had fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ere this in the Bible alſo thoſe facions in teching of pleaſant varietie, whiche thei ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile at in theſe deceiptful naughtie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of error. Thei praiſe the fine diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of philoſophers touching Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. But <hi>Cicero</hi> in his firſt boke <hi>De ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore. Though al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rage ther at, yet wil I (ſaith he) ſpeake as I thinke: By Hercules that one litle boke of the twelue tables, if a man will ſee the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and chiefe pointes of the lawe, ſemeth to me bothe for their aucthoritie, and profite, farre to paſſe all that euer the Philoſophers wrote.</hi> And who knoweth not the ten preceptes of gods law to excede the .xij. tables a M. folde? So then, be theſe boſters of vaine philo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſophie neuer ſo angry, yeat will I alſo ſaie that I thinke, &amp; beleue to be true: that one briefe treatiſe of the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, or boke of Deuterono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, touching the foundacion, principall partes, and effecte of the lawes, farre to ſurmounte in grauitie, and profite at the writinges of all the Phiſoſophers.
<pb facs="tcp:21317:50"/> In the booke of Iob, wiſe, and Godlie menne diſpute very finelie, to whome if you compare the perſones in <hi>Plato,</hi> or <hi>Cicero,</hi> you ſhall ſee in reſpecte thei bee right naught: whiche Hierome alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing ſaieth. <hi>The booke of IOB determineth all matiers with Logiqual propoſicion, aſſumption confirmation, and concluſion.</hi> One Epiſtle of the moſte eloquent Paule, Peter, and Ihon, hathe in it more true holineſſe, and learning, then all the Epiſtles of all the Philoſophers. Neither dooe wee lacke right excellent Oratours, as <hi>Eſaie Micheas, Ioel, Oſeas,</hi> with many other mo, whiche haue left vnto vs moſte profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, cunning, and elegant oracions. You merueile at the thundering woordes of <hi>Pericles,</hi> the Eloquence of <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> and <hi>Cicero.</hi> Thei be reported to haue moued the mindes of the hearers, and enforced theim to what thei woulde. If this bee ſo praiſe worthie, what ſaie you to our Paule, which with bolde, and chereful countenaunce, though he ſtode in irons before the mightie, and learned King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> before the Princes of <hi>Syria,</hi> and before <hi>Feſtus</hi> himſelf preſidente of Iurie,
<pb facs="tcp:21317:50"/> ſo learnedlie, and plainlie pleaded his owne cauſe, and that in a matier of deth and for a religion hated of all men, that King <hi>Agrippa</hi> himſelfe rauiſhed in his wittes cried out ſaiyng. <hi>Thou haſt almoſte made me a Chriſtian man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actes. xxvi.</note> And <hi>Feſtus</hi> himſelf ouercome with his moſt pure, and clere oration, ſaied with a loude voice, <hi>Paule, thou arte beſides thy ſelfe, moche Learning hath made the madde.</hi> Yeat was this <hi>Feſtus</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vneloquent, nor yet vnlearned, nor one that hated the ſtudie of philoſophie I praie you in ſoche an audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in ſuch hate of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſo heinous complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of falſe accuſers, beſides this in a matier of death alſo, yea, &amp; in irons to, what woulde <hi>Cicero</hi> your prince of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence haue doen?<note place="margin">Cicero</note> Without doubt his ſpirite ſtopped vp for feare, ſcarce ſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingly could he haue brought furth one word. For vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a time, as <hi>Plutarche</hi> reher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth, neither bounde, nor led in chaines but borne into the court hall in a ſofte chariot, to pleade not his owne matier, nor a matier of death, but for <hi>Milo,</hi> when he ſawe <hi>Pompeies</hi> armed menne ſtanding rounde about in bright harneſſe, he was
<pb facs="tcp:21317:51"/> amaſed, and confounded, &amp; at laſt trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, &amp; ſcarſe bringing out one worde he began fearfully not to ſpeake, but to ſobbe. Beſides this we haue wiſedome couered alſo in goodly Allegories, as fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiue ceremonies, parables, &amp; canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: wher you ſhal find more miſteries bothe honeſt, and profitable, than in all the vngodlie verſes, whiche al the min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrelles, and Harpers haue ſong in the praiſe, and honour of their wine God Bacchus. In dede thei trimme vp their fables with alluring woordes, and yeat geue you a ſwearde laied ouer with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. Moſt part of their writinges be of deflouring virgines, adulterie, lecherie, deceipte, crueltie, murther, vainglorie, &amp; thinges not to be ſpoken of. But our Poeme is pure, cleane, and honeſt with out all ieopardie. Who euer ſpake or wrote more finely, and wiſely, then our Solomon? Of whome we reade in the thirde boke of Kinges, the fowerth chapiter. <hi>And GOD gaue Sapience, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to SOLOMON aboue meaſure, and a breadth of harte as the ſande of the Sea. And his wiſedome excelled al the wiſedome of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb facs="tcp:21317:51"/> of the Eaſt, and of Egypte. For of all mortalle menne he was the wiſeſt. And there came of all Nacions, and Regions of the Worlde to heare his wiſedome that was ſo moche spoken of.</hi> Yea, the Quene of <hi>SABA</hi> in Riche apparaile, and of wonderful wiſedome came alſo and when ſhe had communed with him of al matiers, and perceiued how he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned his Citie, and Houſholde, ſhee ſaied.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fame that I hearde in my lande of thine Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and Wiſedome, is true, but I woulde not beleue it, till I came my ſelfe, and ſee with mine yies. And yet lo, no not the one haulfe of thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers is tolde me, thou ſo excelleste in Wiſedome, and paſseſt all that is ſpoken of the.</hi> Theſe moſt ſureſt praiſes of our wiſedome no man merueileth at, and yeat we wonder at certeine fables, and vaine thinges, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che very vain liers haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vain Philoſophers: Namely of <hi>Appolonius,</hi> how he wente into <hi>Perſia,</hi> and ſo ouer the Mounteine <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> through the <hi>Albanes, Scythians, Maſsagetes,</hi> thoſe riche Kingdomes of Iude, and paſſing ouer the greate Riuer <hi>PHYSON,</hi> at laſte
<pb facs="tcp:21317:52"/> came to the Brachmans, &amp; all to heare Iarchas ſittyng in his golden throne, and drinkyng of the fountaine Tanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, and diſputyng emong a fewe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones of the nature and properties of natural thinges. We rather wonder at the great deſires of Pythagoras and Plato, of whiche that one is reported to haue gone to Egypt, that other to the Prophetes of Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phis, by a paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full waie, &amp; ieopardeous iourney. Sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſtil here a little I praie you, and learne to be madde and wiſe together. You thinke theim praiſe worthie, and moche to be made of, which toke a farre iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to certaine wiſe men I wotte not who, to learne of them I wot not what but theſe our men you neglect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, &amp; yet of them to be taught all the whole worlde made haſte to come, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thei knew that the high God had there ſet vp his throne &amp; chaire of moſt excellent and perfecte wiſedome. And why folow not you their exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſo greatlie praiſe, and moche mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile at? Now as touching an hiſtorie, is there any like ours, ſo auncient, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:21317:52"/> ſure, ſo graue, ſo profitable? Cicero in his booke, <hi>De oratore,</hi> ſaieth: <hi>An hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie is the witneſſe of time, the light of truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtorie.</note> 
               <hi>the life of remembraunce, the maiſtreſſe of liuyng, the meſsenger of Antiquitie.</hi> And if this be ſo, I maie ſaie trulie that none haue an hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie but chriſtien men. As touchyng certaintie of time, you haue nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Olympiades were founde, and thei began but in the time of Eſaie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der king Iothan.<note place="margin">Olympiades when thei firſt began.</note> So theſe your wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters confound many thinges together, and laie them in heapes all out of ordre, breaking of their matier with vaine fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe fables, the Grecians eſpeciallie, which ſtudied not trueth, but rather to lie, and therfore are condemned of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero, Quintilian, and Iuuenal. <hi>Lodoui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus viues</hi> ſpeakyng plainelie, ſaieth: ſome for feare of reproche, &amp; to lie the more ſafelie, leauyng the Grecians matiers, fette their compaſſe a farre of, from the Perſians, Egiptians, and Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees, as did Herodotus the father of lies, and Diodorus Siculus a triflyng Grecian. Your aucthours alſo write of light matiers neither pleaſaunt nor
<pb facs="tcp:21317:53"/> profitable, and ſette out their bablyng with vaine deſcriptions, &amp; no goodneſſe at all. But our moſte profitable hiſtorie truelie declareth the ordre of times, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the kingdomes one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, &amp; ſpeaketh of nothing without a good reaſon. It maie beſt alſo be called the meſſenger of antiquitie. For beginnyng at the creation of the worlde, it holdeth on to the Monarchie of the Perſians, euen vnto Xerxes. Ioſephus writyng againſt Appion of Alexandria, ſaieth thus: The Greke hiſtoriens, as Acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilaus, and thoſe that folowed him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute the time of Cadmus Mileſius, were but a little before the warres of the Perſians, as witneſſeth <hi>Hellanicus.</hi> So the Greke hiſtorians there began where ours left of. The Latines be moche later. Now then it is plaine whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther our hiſtorie or theirs mai rather be called the meſſenger of Antiquitie. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie, as the holie writers in learnyng and varietie farre paſſe the prophane, ſo in glorie and renoume through al king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of the world, thei excel all other: ſo that to ſaie that
<pb facs="tcp:21317:53"/> Philoſophie is therfore moſt commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, becauſe it hath alwaies bene had in moſte price, is a thing to no purpoſe. The kingdomes of Egypt and Aſſyria were of all the world moſt auncient. In how great eſtimation Ioſeph &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were in that one, it is well knowen. In the other how ſhone our Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie,<note place="margin">Eſai. xxxviii.</note> when as Eſaie Prophecied in one night about the walles of Hieruſalem, were ſlaine an hundred foure ſcore, and v. M. men. To ſpeake nothing of the high aucthoritie of Samuel, Ioſue, and Dauid: <hi>Dooe we not reade of king Solomon, how he was magnified aboue all the kinges of thearth, as well in riches as wiſedome?</hi> And as in the monarchie of Babilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to our Daniel, ſo did Mardocheus rule the whole kingdome of the Medes By the mightieſt kinges of Perſia Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus and Darius great Priuilegies were graunted to our Philoſophers. This is euident in Ioſua, Eſdras, and Nehemias, whiche by fauoure of the princes of Perſia built vp againe both temple &amp; citie. In thempire of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedoniens at the requeſt of Ptolomeus
<pb facs="tcp:21317:54"/> Philadelphus king of Egipt, whiche ſent alſo giftes of incomperable value to the temple of Hieruſalem, our lawe was tranſlated into the Greke tonge. But in the monarchie of the Romains the Bible now diſperſed through the whole worlde ſo willinglie was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of all men, that al whiche had witte and knowlege moſte gladlie badde your deceiptful Philoſophie farewell. Why then go you now about to call it vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine being ones dead and buried? Or what remaineth els, then all lies quite forſaken, to geue our ſelues wholie to be inſtructed in the moſte auncient, certaine, and moſte holeſome Philoſophie of the Bible?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:54"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Londini in</hi> aedibus Richardi Graftoni Reginae a typographia excuſum. Anno Domini. M.D.LIII.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:55"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Richard Grafton, featuring the classical seven sciences or seven libreral arts (McKerrow 122)</figDesc>
               <q>VERSVTVS CELAT SCIENTIAM <bibl>PRO. 12.</bibl>
               </q>
               <p>GRAM</p>
               <p>MVSIC</p>
               <p>ASTRO</p>
               <p>LOG</p>
               <p>GE<hi rend="sup">o</hi>MET</p>
               <p>RETHOR</p>
               <p>ARITHM</p>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:21317:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
